<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Depopulation arraigned, convicted and condemned, by the lawes of God and man a treatise necessary in these times; by R.P. of Wells, one of the Societie of New Inne.</title>
            <author>Powell, Robert, fl. 1636-1652.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1636</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 148 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 76 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09897</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20160</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101175</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836997</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836997</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1301</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09897)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1301)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 970:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Depopulation arraigned, convicted and condemned, by the lawes of God and man a treatise necessary in these times; by R.P. of Wells, one of the Societie of New Inne.</title>
                  <author>Powell, Robert, fl. 1636-1652.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Proceedings. 1631. Nov. 23. Court of Star Chamber.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 118, [26] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R[ichard] B[adger] and are to bee sold in S. Dunstans Church-yard neere the Church doore,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1636.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Rob. Povvell.</note>
                  <note>Economic abuses in British agriculture.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>"In Camera Stellata coram concilio ibidem, vicessimo tertio die Novembris, anno septimo Caroli Regis", I5r-end.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Agriculture --  Economic aspects --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Grain trade --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1301:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1301:1"/>
            <p>DEPOPVLATION ARRAIGNED, CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VICTED AND CONDEM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NED, BY THE LAWES OF GOD and Man: A TREATISE NECESSARY IN THESE TIMES;</p>
            <p>By R. P. of Wells, one of the Societie <hi>of New Inne.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Regis, Eccleſiae, reipublicae, &amp; pauperum ergò.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. B.</hi> and are to bee ſold in S. <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Church-yard neere the Church doore, 1636.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1301:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1301:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL, truly Learned, and moſt <hi>judicious, Sir</hi> Iohn Banks <hi>Knight, Attourney</hi> Generall to the ſacred Majeſty of our Soveraigne Lord <hi>King CHARLES.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worſhipfull,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a true ſaying, that the <hi>lives of ſome men are like a long vacation:</hi> I cannot altogether excuſe my ſelfe of ſome fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe vacancies, and do therfore ſincerely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge my ſelfe a debtor to the Common
<pb facs="tcp:1301:3"/>weale: yet upon the occaſion of ſome im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment by a very worthy friend <hi>Thom. Hughes Eſquire,</hi> in the County, where I live, upon the execution of his Majeſties Commiſsion addreſſed into that, and other ſeverall Counties for the diſcovery, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of a monstrous and growing evill, Depopulation; this ſmall treatiſe, by my ſlender labours of the laſt long vacation, had its conception, birth, and being. A little creature it is, and though it hath obteyned licenſe to walke abroad into the world, yet it cannot be bould without the protection of authority to adventure into the hands of this age for feare of cruſhing. As under his Royall Majeſty, and his moſt honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Privy Councell, it properly apperteyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth unto the eminent truſt of your place to provide for the diſcovery, and prepare for the ſuppreſsion of ſuch, and the like oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions;
<pb facs="tcp:1301:3"/>(wherein your faithfull care, and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilancy hath beene ſufficiently remonstra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) ſo is it moſt proper for your worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to patronize the labours of any well affected Subject in this kinde from the ſpurnings and tramplings of the grander ſort of delinquents. To you therfore Right worſhipfull, this little <hi>one</hi> doth humbly preſent it ſelfe, and earneſtly implores your favourable patronage &amp; ſafe conduct to be vouchſafed to it, wherewith being incoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it will not feare the face of any greedy and grinding <hi>Achabs</hi> or <hi>Nimrods</hi> of the times, it will modeſtly preſume to tell thoſe peop e how injurious they are to his highneſſe royall State in the diminution of his people, in the multitude of whom con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth the honour of a Prince, as alſo in the leſſening of his revenewes: It will tel them, how ſacrilegious they are to the Church and
<pb facs="tcp:1301:4"/>painfull miniſtery: how pernitious they are to the Common weale, and what wretched ſtarvers they are of all ſorts of poore: The criminous actors in this miſchiefe have ſpread themſelves throughout all the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Kingdom, and have ſcattered and diſperſed the many ſamples of their worst actions, as the Levite did the twelve parts of his Concubine <hi>per omnes ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minos,</hi> through all the quarters of Iſrael. I might more aptly ſay that his Majeſty hath dealt in juſtice with this crying crime, as the Levite did in the caſe of his dead Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubine, with the <hi>Gibeathites.</hi> He diſperſed her <hi>membratim,</hi> by pieces and morſels, aſwell for a ſhame, a byword, and a parable againſt the unruly actors in that tragedy, with a <hi>nunquam res talis facta eſt in Iſrael:</hi> As alſo to ſummon a generall aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, for the juſt deſtruction of them; This
<pb facs="tcp:1301:4"/>only puts the difference; there was then no King in Iſrael. Bleſſed be God, we have a bleſſed King over our Iſrael, who (not for deſtruction) for reformation of oppreſsing Depopulators hath by his gratious directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to his honourable Iudges circuiting all the quarters of his Kingdom, ſeconded with his carefull Commiſsions, and by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences inſuing therupon, indeavoured to diſtribute all parts of Royall juſtice in <hi>om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes terminos Iſraelis;</hi> And as the offence of late time hath growne ſo monſtrous, as never was it ſo great, nor ſo exemplary in its evill in any former age: So the unpat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terned proceeding in proportionable Iuſtice by his Majeſtie, and his right honourable Counſell, doth juſtly meet with it: <hi>Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam res talis facta eſt in Iſrael;</hi> Heer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, as in other things your prudent and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident care neither hath been, nor is want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:
<pb facs="tcp:1301:5"/>And that it may long continue, and increaſe with length of happie and honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dayes, he, who beggeth pardon for this preſumption, will not faile to offer up his continuall prayers to Heaven.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips in all obſervance and duty, ROE. POVVELL.</signed>
               <dateline>New Inne <date>
                     <hi>1.</hi> Iuly. <hi>1636.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <opener>
               <date>
                  <hi>Decemb. 3. 1635.</hi>
               </date>
            </opener>
            <p>Perlegi hoc Opuſculum cui Titulus (Depopulation, Arraigned, Convicted, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) quod continet pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginas <hi>64.</hi> in quibus nihil reperio ſanae doctrinae au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bonis moribus contrarium, quo minus cum utilita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te public â imprimi poſſint, ſub eâ tamen conditione ut ſi non intra ſex menſes proxime ſequentes typis mandemur, haec licentia ſit omninò irrita.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Guil. Haywood R. R. P.</hi> Archiepiſc. Cantuar. Capell. domeſt.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1301:5"/>
            <head>Depopulation ARRAIGNED, CONVICTED, AND CONDEMNED.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have in another Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe handled the grand offence of Foreſtal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and Ingroſſers of Corne, and therein touched his Highneſſe carefull di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, and juſt proceeding, againſt them; I ſhall now preſume to adde one debt more unto the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his Majeſties many and memorable deeds of impartiall <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,</hi> his zealous and indefatigable care often commended, and charged to his Counſellors of State, for roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1301:6"/>up and extirpation of that cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſinne <hi>Depopulation,</hi> and the thrice honourable proceedings of his high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt judicatorie Court againſt ſome delinquents, and his Majeſties no leſſe goodnes in addreſſing ſeverall Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions (according to former preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, of his moſt noble progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors) into moſt part of his kingdome, for the more abſolute diſcovery of this monſtrous overgrowne evill, which I may well terme <hi>peccatum Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melinum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label> It is an offence at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law: For ſo it appeares by the Statute of 39<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. ELIZ. 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. (hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cited at large) that the decaies of townes and habitations, have beene, by the ancient lawes of this Realme, eſteemed an high offence. And by the decree of the Starre-Chamber, which I ſhall handle in its due place, Offences of that nature are puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhable at the common-Law. That it is a publike and popular offence, who can deny? Then being popular, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1301:6"/>an offence at the Common-Law, it might and may bee inquired at the ancient Courts of <hi>Leet</hi> or view of <hi>Franckplegde.</hi> And though it be now in this age growne Gyant-like with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a proper name, ſave what the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable iſſue and fruit of its prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous birth doth render <hi>(Depopulation;)</hi> and though by connivence and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punity in former times, it is now growne ſo huge, that the proportion of remedy muſt exceed the ordinary verge of Iuſtice, and appeale to the higheſt ſeat, yet fit it is, that the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery thereof ſhould be revived, and injoyned within the inquiſition of the <hi>Leet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> The inquiry of Foreſtallers, and ſuch like miſcreants, began to languiſh and to bee diſuſed in thoſe Courts, untill his Majeſties gracious directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons did put life into it. And certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if the inquiry of this growing evill had at thoſe ancient meetings beene from time to time obſerved, it had not mounted to ſo monſtrous a growth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:1301:7"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>3</label> Whether the <hi>Foreſtaller</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſſer,</hi> or the <hi>Depopulator,</hi> be the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vieſt in the ſcale, both being the ſpawne of that bloud-ſucking <hi>Cyno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myia</hi> covetouſneſſe, might at firſt apprehenſion ſeeme doubtfull; But if, to ſhut and cloſe up the wombe of the earth, <hi>communis reipublicae matris,</hi> from bringing forth any increaſe at all, bee a worſe ſinne than the hiding and hoarding up of her fruits after it's birth; then is the one more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitious and intolerable then the other, both too bad, neither of them worthy of the leaſt indulgence, for both are horribly guilty of privative injuſtice. And if the curſe be denounced againſt that, <hi>Qui abſcondit frumentum maledi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cetur in populo, Pro.</hi> 11.26. it muſt needs, fall heavier upon this. <hi>Depopu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> is <hi>praefocatio matricis,</hi> a ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling or choaking of the wombe, and cauſing an utter ſterility. The other foreſtalling and ingroſſing, is <hi>ſuffura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio partus matricis,</hi> a privie ſtealer (though a publike enemy) of the birth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1301:7"/>of the wombe, both Monopoliſts, and both Foſter-fathers of miſerable Famine, this preventing a plenty, that raiſing a dearth, and ſcarcity in the time of plenty.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>4</label> I am not here to deale with thoſe, whom the <hi>Civilians</hi> call <hi>Nocturnos Depopulatores agrorum,</hi> invaders of other mens poſſeſſions in the night, whom it was lawfull to kill if they reſiſted, <hi>Liceat occidere propria autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate;</hi> but with an offendor of a farre worſe nature. That being an open enemy, may be eaſily reſiſted or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented: this under a Maſke and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of his owne private, deſtroyeth the publike good. It is like the biting of an Aſpe, a little Serpent in <hi>Affrick,</hi> which takes away the life of him whom it bites in a kinde of ſwowne, <hi>ſenſibus ſinè ſenſu deficientibus.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I can well proceed in deciphering the odious conditions of that abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſinne of <hi>Depopulation,</hi> I muſt render a definition and deſcription of it. The word is not obvious to the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1301:8"/>underſtanding of thoſe whom it moſt concernes and offends, that is, his Highneſſe liege people, verſed and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in rurall affaires of Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>5</label>
               <hi>Depopulation</hi> hath its <hi>Etymon</hi> from the prepoſition <hi>De,</hi> and the verbe <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulor,</hi> which ſinglie ſignifies and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports to robbe and ſpoile people, to waſte and deſtroy Countryes. <hi>Seneca</hi> tells us, <hi>Cura populatur artus,</hi> Care con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumeth the joynts: and it is aggravated by the word <hi>(De)</hi> which imports ablatively, in and by ſome unlawfull act, and the conſequence and effects of that unlawfull act, by the privation of ſome lawfull and common good.</p>
            <p>To deſcribe it more plainely, it robbes and pilles the people of their due meanes and maintenance, and thereby diſables them both in body and ſtate from performing their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and leige obedience, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately to their Prince, and mediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Common-weale; By which I meane, Clergy, and Laiety: And it
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1301:8"/>alters the quality of the people; from good Husbands, it makes them houſeleſſe and thriftleſſe, puts them in a courſe of idleneſſe (the mother of miſchiefe, and bane of all rule and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.) So as they become aliens and ſtrangers to their nationall govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the kingdome by that meanes in a manner diſpeopled and deſolated.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>6</label> The unlawfull wayes and meanes by which this grievous deſolation is wrought, are next to be conſidered; It is not by any invaſion, ſacking or ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacking of places or people, by any forraigne enemy, but by a boſome and home-bred enemy, either by an actuall, violent, and voluntary raſing and demolition of manſions and hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of habitation, or a careleſſe and negligent ſuffering of them to decay, and to bee unhabitable, or by inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and hedging in Common fields, and converting errable into paſture.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect </seg>7</label> The Perſons Actors in this op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion are (though they draw in by
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1301:9"/>their example other inferior perſons) griping and avaritious Land-lords, who commonly ſuffer ancient demi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeable tenements, to fall into their hands, and ſo retaine them without granting further eſtates, at conſciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fines; and then wilfully, or negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently decay the houſes, and either keepe their grounds in their owne, or a Bay liffes manurance, or let it out by ſeverall parcells, at rack and extreame rents, to ſeverall perſons; who to make the beſt of a bad bargaine, are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced (for want of the entierty of a Meſſuage, or farme to maintaine a Plough.) to turne Tillage into pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, and thereby onely keepe a few Sheepe and a Cow.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>8</label> The ſubject of this ſinne is, hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and lands. A houſe by the <hi>Civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> is called <hi>Manſus,</hi> and doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of foundation, wall and cover; in our French Law <hi>Maiſon,</hi> and in our legall latine <hi>Meſſuagium,</hi> which containes the buildings, Curtilage, Orchard, and Garden; and Meſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1301:9"/>conſiſts of two things, land and ſtructure. And though before the building, it was but land, yet when the edifice is erected, then is it cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Meſſuage: And albeit the ſtructure bee afterwards utterlie ruinated, <hi>Et aequata ſolo,</hi> yet for dignities ſake, in regard it was once a place of habitation, which is high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſteemed in the Law, it ſhall have no more the name of Land, but bee called a TOFTE, (that is) a place wherein a houſe had beene.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>9</label> Land or earth, <hi>Terra</hi> in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall ſence is taken for the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme of mortality, <hi>terra quam ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimus,</hi> The earth or earthly Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle of our fleſh, which wee beare about us, and which muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to earth. In the interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Law it doth compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend any ground, ſoyle or earth whatſoever, and is the moſt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall name of all ſorts of ſoyle: But properly, <hi>Terra dicitur à terendo.</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:1301:10"/>The earth on which wee tread and walke, and muſt make uſe of the fruits and increaſe thereof, to ſuſtaine and ſupport our houſes of clay, and yet more ſpecially <hi>à terendo, quia vomere teritur,</hi> broken, bruized, and worne with the plough-ſhare.</p>
            <p>As the Heavens are the habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Almighty God; ſo the earth hath hee appointed as the ſuburbs of Heaven, to be the habitation of man. <hi>Behold the Heaven, and the Heaven of Heavens is the Lords, the earth alſo with all that therein is, Deuteronomie</hi> 10. ver. 14.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>10</label>
               <hi>Agricolari fuit hominum prima conditio &amp; ſtatus:</hi> even before the fall, God tooke <hi>Adam,</hi> and put him into the Garden of <hi>Eden</hi> to dreſſe it and to keep it, <hi>Poſuit in paradiſum voluptat is, ut operaretur &amp; cuſtodiret illum.</hi> After the fall and the expulſion of our firſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, it was then <hi>primum opus homini impoſitum propter peccatum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Agriculture was the firſt worke injoyned to man for ſinne: God then
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1301:10"/>gave the earth to man with limitation and condition, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Curſed is the ground for thy ſake, in ſorrow ſhalt thou eat of it all the dayes of thy life.</hi> 19. <hi>In the ſweat of thy face ſhalt thou eate bread, untill thou returne unto the ground: for out of it waſt thou taken; for duſt thou art, and unto duſt ſhalt thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne:</hi> And it followes. 23. <hi>The Lord God ſent him forth to till the ground from whence he was taken, Vt operaretur terram de qua ſumptus eſt.</hi> The gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing of heards, of beaſts, and ſheepe, are part of Husbandry; <hi>Pars ruſticae vitae, in illis qui armenta &amp; oves paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunt, conſiſtere videtur,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, li.</hi> 24. <hi>Syntag. cap.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adams</hi> two ſonnes, <hi>Abel</hi> and <hi>Cain,</hi> were both Husband-men, <hi>Abelcuſtos ovium, Cain agricola,</hi> the one a keeper of Sheep, the other a Tiller of ground; and there were houſes, habitations, and Citties built by them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>11</label> So we ſee God gave the earth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to man, <hi>terram dedit filiſs hominum. But God ſaw the wickedneſſe of man was
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1301:11"/>great in the earth, Gen.</hi> 6.5. He ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by a generall deluge over the face of the whole earth, doth cancell his former gift of <hi>terram dedit,</hi> with a <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſo</hi> of preſervation reſerved to <hi>Noah</hi> and them that were with him in the <hi>Arke, Gen.</hi> 7.23. But after the waters had prevailed upon the earth an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and fifty dayes, <hi>Geneſis</hi> 8.1. <hi>God remembred Noah and every living thing, and all the cattell that was with him in the Arke: And God made a winde to paſſeover the earth, and the waters aſſwaged;</hi> And afterwards <hi>the face of the ground was dry, Noah and his family by Gods direction went forth.</hi> 20.21. <hi>And every beaſt, every creeping thing, and every foule, and whatſoever creepeth upon the earth, after their kinds, went forth out of the Arke. And Noah builded an Altar unto the Lord and tooke of every cleane beaſt, and of every cleane foule, and offered burnt offerings on the Altar;</hi> God accepted the ſweet favour of <hi>Noahs</hi> thankfull ſacrifice, and reneweth his former
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1301:11"/>grant of <hi>terram dedit</hi> by a ſtrict cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. <hi>Nonigitur ultra percutiam omnem animam viventem, ſicut feci,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I will not againe ſmite any more every living thing as I have done: Cunctis diebus ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae, while the earth remaineth, ſeed time and harveſt, and cold and heat, and Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and winter, and day and night ſhall not ceaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>12</label> Thus man by Gods covenants ſtands ſeized of an abſolute inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in fee of the earth, the beſt of the foure elements, <hi>Habendum per ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitia, To hold in capite of Almighty God,</hi> as of his Throne of Heaven, to which the earth is but a footſtoole, and to uſes too, <hi>diſpenſatores, non diſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patores;</hi> To be Stewards of it, <hi>terram colere, aras excolere,</hi> to till, manure and husband the earth, and out of the increaſe thereof to build, poliſh and repaire <hi>Altars, Churches and Oratories for the God of Iſrael,</hi> and to maintaine and ſupport the beauty of holineſſe, and to give unto Gods Miniſters, the ſacred <hi>Prieſt-hood,</hi> his owne reſerved
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1301:12"/>portion, their dues and duties, and not to commit any ſpoile, waſte or deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the earth, or the inhabitants thereof. Thus wee obſerve that the firſt inſtitution of Husbandry upon the earth, injoyned by God for the ſin of man, was <hi>agriculture, tillage,</hi> and muſt bee performed by the worke of the hands, and ſweat of the brow; the maintenance of the Oxe at the crib, and the paſturage of the Sheepe, are but handmaids to doe their office in that great labour, <hi>The Oxe to plough the ground, the ſheepe to compeſter it in due times of ſeaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>13</label> The end and fruit of <hi>Tillage,</hi> is to bring <hi>food out of the earth, and bread to ſtrengthen mans heart, Pſalm.</hi> 104.15. all ſorts of victuall or ſuſtenance, either, oyle, wine, or any other foode are inferiour to bread. When God pronounceth any commination of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine for the wickedneſe of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, it is by breaking the ſtaffe of bread, <hi>Ecce ego conteram baculum panis in</hi> Hieruſalem; <hi>Ezec.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Behold I
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1301:12"/>will breake the ſtaffe of bread in Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, and they ſhall eat bread by weight and with care, and they ſhall drinke wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by meaſure and with aſtoniſhment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>14</label> This worke of <hi>agriculture</hi> hath bin univerſally eſteemed in all nations of the world. Among the heathen Idolaters (who had a glimmering of a deity) many of them in the variety of objects finding contentment to their deſires, forthwith collected that to be God, which had given them ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment, from whence ſprang <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</hi> The earth and the fruits thereof were had in ſo great honour, that they aſcribed a kind of deity to it. Let me a little proſecute the fictious alluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Heathen Poets in this kinde, that I may convince the earth-choaking Chriſtians of this age: they feigne <hi>Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> (further they doe not aſpire) to be married to <hi>Terra</hi> his ſiſter, by ſome called <hi>Veſta, ſive quòd omnibus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus terra veſtiatur, ſive quòd vi ſua ſtet;</hi> either becauſe the earth is cloathed with all things, or becauſe it ſubſiſteth
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1301:13"/>of its own ſtrength. The latter ſeemes to be borrowed from <hi>Ovid, Lib:</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Stat viterra ſua,<note place="margin">Ovid l. <hi>3.</hi> Faſt.</note> vi ſtando, veſta vocatur.</q>
            <p>But the firſt in my judgement is more probable. For <hi>veſture</hi> (<hi>veſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi>) ſignifies a garment, and in that ſence it may be taken; for graſſe, corne and all kinde of Trees, Woods, and under-woods, are as it were the come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly clothing and garments of the earth. I finde in an old Law of King <hi>Inas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lambert Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaion.</note> which herein I ſhall have occaſion to touch: <hi>Qui decem hidas terrae occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verit, ſex hidas frugibus veſtito.</hi> In the uſe of our common Law, it is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken metaphorically to betoken a poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, or an admittance to a poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; and with the feudiſts, poſſeſſion it ſelfe. And ſo it may well ſtand ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Gods grant before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; <hi>terram dedit filijs hominum.</hi> Sometimes it is taken for the profits of the land: And ſo 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. ED. 1. Stat. 1. intituled <hi>extenta manerij;</hi> Inquirie was to be made <hi>pro quanto veſtura cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſlibet
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1301:13"/>acre poſsit communiter appreciari,</hi> how much the veſture of an acre is worth. But I returne to my poeticall pedigree: They further feigne, that in this marriage <hi>Saturnus. Atlas, Ops,</hi> and others, brothers and ſiſters were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten: And from the name of <hi>Coelus</hi> they derive the appellation of the higheſt heavens: <hi>Ab cujus nomine miravarietate formoſiſsimum, ſupremum Corpus coelum dicunt fuiſſe appellatum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some thinke that <hi>Ops</hi> the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was ſo called; <hi>Quod terrae ope vita hominum ſustentatur,</hi> by the helpe of the earth, the life of man is ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; or from the ancient adjective <hi>Ops,</hi> which fignified rich. For the people of ancient dayes, whoſe riches did e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially conſiſt in <hi>Agriculture</hi> and cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, did adore the earth by the name of the goddeſſe <hi>Ops,</hi> as the bountifull Miſtreſſe of their wealth; they alſo feigne <hi>Ceres</hi> to be the daughter of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne and <hi>Ops,</hi> and to be the firſt Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix of fruit and tillage, whence <hi>Virgil.</hi> 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Geo.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:1301:14"/>
               <l>Prima Ceres ferre mortales vertere ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram</l>
               <l>Inſtituit—</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Ceres</hi> did firſt direct the uſe of Iron Plow.</p>
            <p>This goddeſſe was ſometimes called <hi>Theſmophoros (i.e.) legum latrix.</hi> For ſome would have the originall of lawes, for metes and boundaries, and right of property, to begin with the uſe of Tillage and Husbandry: <hi>Coep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt de agrorum finibus (qui antea nulli erant) diſceptari:</hi> Then the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits and bounds of fields (which were not before) began to be in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion. And certaine it is, the occaſion of Tillage and Corne, begat the more frequent uſe of diſtinctions, Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markes and boundaries.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>15</label> As I ſaid before, the people in thoſe blind dayes, were ready to make a god of that, which gave them a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent content. <hi>Dimenſiones terrarum terminis, poſitis vagantibus ac diſcordan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1301:14"/>populis pacis utilia praeſtiterunt:</hi> The allotting and bounding of land, did yeeld the profitableneſſe of peace, unto wandring and diſagreeing peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. The luxuriant fruition of peace, by this meanes made them fancy, and frame to themſelves the worſhip of an <hi>Idoll</hi> called <hi>Terminus,</hi> to whom they offered up their ſacrifices in the month of February; <hi>Numa Pompilius</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond King of the Romans after <hi>Romu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> having made a publike perambula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion throughout the kingdome, and prefixed private limitations and bounds, betwixt party and party; did for eſtabliſhment thereof dedicate a Chappell, upon the top of the <hi>Tarpei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Hill unto this <hi>Idoll;</hi> to whom the people by way of ſacrifice brought Cakes, pulſe, and the firſt fruits of the field. In the embleme of peace, <hi>Agri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culture</hi> is pourtrayed as her Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſiſter, and daughter, carrying eares of corne, and grapes in her hand.</p>
            <q>Quae comes haec ſpicas manibus quae ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtat, &amp; uvas.</q>
            <q>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:1301:15"/>
               <l>Agricultura, quid illa?</l>
               <l>Fida comes pacis, ſoror haec, &amp; filia,—</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>16</label>
               <hi>Licurgus</hi> of <hi>Sparta,</hi> the <hi>Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> Law maker, obſerving what great emolument the ſtudy and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of husbandry did afford unto the publike Weale, did divide and farme out all his fields unto his Citizens; that thereby laying aſide all private envy and grudge, they might all alike ſhare in paines and profit together.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cato</hi> the elder was wont to ſay, that the choiſeſt men for ſtrength and martiall deſignes, and that imagined leaſt miſchiefe, had their off ſpring from Husbandmen, <hi>ex agricolis naſci.</hi> It is reported by <hi>Suetonius,</hi> that when <hi>Domiti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the Emperour, taking notice that <hi>ſtudio colendi vineta, negligerentur arva;</hi> the ſollicitous care in pruning, and trimming of Vineyards begat a neglect of tillage, commanded all the vines to be rooted out and deſtroyed. The remedy was as bad as the evill; his care of husbandry (had it beene
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1301:15"/>ſingly) was commendable, but not his abſolute deſtruction of Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards; which was a type of his blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy perſecution of Chriſtians, and was intolerable to the weale publike.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the <hi>Romans, Agriculture</hi> grew in ſo high eſteeme, that the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nators themſelves would put their hands to the plow. And it never pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpered better, than when the Senators themſelves plowed: <hi>Scipio major</hi> is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by <hi>Seneca,</hi> often to have exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed himſelfe in Tillage, <hi>Vt mos erat priſcis,</hi> as the cuſtome was; and was wont after he had tyred himſelfe with rurall labours, to refreſh his body by bathing, <hi>abluere corpus ruſticis feſſum laboribus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The beſt of ancient <hi>Orators,</hi> in deſcribing of liberall,<note place="margin">Cic. l. <hi>1.</hi> Offi.</note> and illiberall arts and ſciences, tells us, That <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium rerum ex quibus aliquid exquiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, nihil agricultura melius, nihil uberi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, nihil dulcius, nihil libero homine dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius:</hi> Nothing better, nothing more plentifull, more ſweet, more worthy
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1301:16"/>of a free man, than Tillage.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>17</label> Let us ſurvey the high eſteeme of <hi>Agriculture,</hi> and Tillage, by the line and levell of the ancient government in this kingdome. Amongſt the lawes of King <hi>Inas,</hi> whom I mentioned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and who began his raigne in the yeare of Chriſt 712. the 65 Law is <hi>de fundum occupantibus,</hi> and is to this purpoſe;<note place="margin">Archaion.</note> 
               <hi>Qui viginiti hidas ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae poſſederit, is migraturus undecim hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das ſegetibus ſatas à tergo relinquito: Qui decem occupârit, is ſex hidas frugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus veſtito,</hi> &amp;c. Hee that was poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of twenty hides of land, and was to depart thence to dwell elſewhere, ſhould leave behind him twelve hides ſowne with corne: And he that had ten, ſhould leave ſixe, and ſo after the like proportion. By this may bee collected, what provident care thoſe times had for maintenance of the Plow and Tillage.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>18</label> The firſt commencement of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon appendment by the ancient Law of this Realme, was to maintaine the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1301:16"/>ſervice of the Plow, <hi>ſervitium ſocae.</hi> And therefore the Tenant had common in the Lords waſts, to gaine (<hi>i. e</hi> to till) and to compeſter the land, for the maintenance of tillage; which was much regarded and favoured by the Law. This ſort of land was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently called hide and gaine, the word hide ſignifying ſuch a portion of land, as might be laboured and til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in a yeare, and a day, by one Plow: and gaine (<hi>i. e. Quaeſtus, lucrum;</hi>) Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonymically from the profit and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage which ariſeth by Tillage; whence the <hi>Civilians</hi> do terme Corne and harveſt fruits, <hi>Fructus induſtriales.</hi> And whereas all ſervice due for land, is either Knights ſervice or ſocage: The word ſocage is derived of the word <hi>ſoc (i. e.) vomer</hi> a Plow-ſhare or Coulter. <hi>Et inde</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bracton li.</hi> 2. <hi>ca.</hi> 35. <hi>num.</hi> 1.) <hi>tenentes qui tenent in ſockagio ſockmanni dici poterunt; co quòd deputati ſunt (ut videtur) tantum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo ad culturam.</hi> The tenure of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cage hath more priviledges than that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1301:17"/>of Knights ſervice. The ſonne and heire of a ſocage tennant, <hi>ſockmanni,</hi> was underſtood to be of ſufficient age to enter to his land <hi>cum quindecim com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleverit annos,</hi> whereas the ſonne and heire of the other, not till hee attaine the age of 21. <hi>Glanvill lib.</hi> 7. <hi>ca.</hi> 9.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>19</label> The common Law did and doth preferre errable land before all other ſort of land. And therefore for its dignity is named in a <hi>Praecipe</hi> upon a fine, and in a writ of entry, before mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, paſture, wood, or any other ſoyle.</p>
            <p>Yea the very beaſt of the Plow, <hi>averia carucae</hi> have a priviledge. For in the old Statute, <hi>de diſtrictione Scac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carij.</hi> 51. <hi>Hen.</hi> 3.1266. It is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided that no man of Religion (or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) ſhall be diſtreyned by his beaſts that gaine his land, nor by his Sheepe for the Kings debt, nor the debt of any other man, nor for any other cauſe, by the Kings, or other Bayliffes; but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they can finde another diſtreſſe, or Chattells ſufficient, whereof they
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1301:17"/>may levie the debt, or that is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for the demand, except impoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of beaſts, damage Fezant. By the Statute of <hi>Artic. ſuper chartas</hi> 28<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. EDW. 1. <hi>ca.</hi> 12. The King willed, that diſtreſſes to be taken for his debts, ſhould not be made upon beaſts of the Plow, ſo long as a man may finde any other; upon this Law a writ is foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>ne quis diſtring atur per averia ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rucarum, vel per oves ſuas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Regiſt. Brev.</note> againſt thoſe that ſhall tranſgreſſe, and impound any cattell of the Plow, or ſheepe, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to that ordinance being made; <hi>ad communem utilitatem Regnì,</hi> as the writ ſets forth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>20</label> To compare the Lawes of other Nations, amongſt the ancient <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Agricolae</hi> were the ſecond degree of men, after the Philoſophers or wiſe men. And when all the Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in that great Country (being by ſome noted to be the third part of all the earth, containing 50000. Townes) were imbroyled with civill Warres; amidſt all their hoſtilities,<note place="margin">Strah. li. <hi>55.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:1301:18"/>
               <hi>Agricolae erant ſacroſancti &amp; intacti, agri<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> corum,</hi> &amp;c. the Husbandmen and their fields, were priviledged from any violation or invaſion, and they had the happineſſe, quietly to apply themſelves unto their Plow, their vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, lopping of trees, or their harveſt labours, according to the ſeaſon of the yeare: <hi>Arrianus in Indicis.</hi> Whence it may be probably conceived that the induſtry of the people, as well as the fertility of the ſoyle was the meanes, that the earth in thoſe parts brought forth its fruits to maturity twice a yeare. This cuſtom of the <hi>Indians</hi> grew to bee part of the Civill Law among the <hi>Romans, li.</hi> 2. <hi>Synt. Tit.</hi> 27<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>21</label> It was the conſtitution of <hi>Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus Caeſar;</hi> which meetely ſympho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizeth with our common Law, <hi>Agri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultores circa rem ruſticam occupati, dum villis inſident, dum agros colunt, ſecuri ſint in quacun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> parte terrarum: ita ut nullus inveniatur tam audax, ut perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas, boves, &amp; agrorum inſtrumenta, aut ſi quid aliud ſit, quod ad agrorum ruſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1301:18"/>curam pertineat, invadere, aut cape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, aut violenter auferre praeſumat:</hi> That Husbandmen verſed about their Country affaires, whileſt they abode upon their farmes, and whileſt they tilled their grounds, ſhould be quiet, or ſafe in all parts of the land. So, that none ſhould be ſo hardy, as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to aſſault, take, or forcibly carry away, their perſons, their Oxen, and tooles of Husbandry, or any other thing that belonged to the affaires of Husbandry. The penalty followeth, and deſerves a due perpenſion: <hi>Si quis autem hujuſmodi ſtatutum auſu temera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio violare praeſumpſerit, in quadruplum ablata reſtituat, &amp; infamiae notam ipſo jure incurrat, imperiali arbitrio nihilomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus puniendus:</hi> The raſh and inſolent violater of that Law was to make a fourefold reſtitution of the things ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, to be accounted infamous by the Law, and notwithſtanding to be puniſhed at the pleaſure of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour. I ſhall in its proper place, parallell the late Decree of the Kings
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1301:19"/>great counſell, and high Court of Starre-chamber againſt <hi>Depopulation,</hi> with this imperiall conſtitution for rurall immunities, to ſhew that no Law or ordinance never ſo ſtrictly contrived, hath beene hitherto more proportionably and conveniently medicinable for this ſore then the Arbitrary proceedings of that great Court.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>22</label> The benefit and commodity of tillage, and ſupporting houſes of Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry, will beſt bee manifeſted by deſcribing the inconvenience of <hi>Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulation, Contraria contrarijs illuſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> And therein I ſhall not need to inquire any further, than into the Statute Lawes of our kingdome, and to take a ſurvey, as well of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ambles, and the reaſons therein com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed, which are <hi>Medulla legis,</hi> as of the <hi>proviſo</hi> or act it ſelfe, which is (I may terme it) <hi>medicina mali;</hi> where the ſymptomes and circumſtances of diſeaſes, either corporall or politicall, are not firſt diſcried, the remedy may
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1301:19"/>be miſapplyed. In this caſe therefore <hi>Optima ſtatuti interpres eſt (omnibus par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulis ejuſdem inſpectis) ipſum ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>King Henry</hi> the ſeventh,<note place="margin">Lord Bacon.</note> by an eminent writer of his life, is highly commended for the lawes enacted in his time, to advance Husbandry and tillage; Though the common Law, at that time, was furniſhed with ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient power to defend and conſerve it, and to puniſh the delinquents; yet that being <hi>lex non ſcripta,</hi> was not ſo conſpicuous to the vulgar eie, as an act of Parliament made by all the three States; whereof, as every man hath by his ſuffrage of electing of Knights and Burgeſſes, an intereſt in the making of it, ſo he may the ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner take notice of it. And therefore to prevent the then growing evill, the firſt poſitive Law was made in the third Parliament,<note place="margin">4 <hi>He.</hi> 7. <hi>ca.</hi> 19.</note> holden in the fourth yeare of his raigne, <hi>ca.</hi> 19<hi rend="sup">0</hi>. providing penalties againſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caying houſes of Husbandrie, or
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1301:20"/>not laying of convenient land for the maintenance of the ſame:<note place="margin">Eodem Anno. ca. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> But I muſt looke backe upon another Statute, the ſame time, <hi>Cap.</hi> 12<hi rend="sup">0</hi> which was made to rowze up the remiſſe and miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaning Iuſtices of peace of that age, with more care to execute their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, to redreſſe injuries, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the lawes, which is termed by that learned Writer, Monitory and Minatory. And therein amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther enormities, which did daily ariſe by the impunity of murders, robbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, felonies, idleneſſe, extortions, and other offences, it is expreſſed, that the Husbandry of this land was decai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, whereby</p>
            <p>The Church of England was upholden,</p>
            <p>The ſervice of GOD continued,</p>
            <p>Every man thereby had his ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,</p>
            <p>Every inheritor his rent for his land.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty then did therein fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther declare his conſideration, that a
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1301:20"/>great part of the wealth, and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his land, did depend upon the increaſing and upholding of Husban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry. This Statute is but by way of reflexion, and ſtrikes at this evill, but through the ſides of the Iuſtices.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>23</label> That which followes, did ſtrike more home to it <hi>(i. e.)</hi> the Statute <hi>ca.</hi> 19<hi rend="sup">0</hi>. which ſets forth; That among all other things, great inconveniences did daily increaſe by deſolation and pulling downe, and by wilfull waſte of houſes and Townes within the Realme, and laying to paſture, lands which cuſtomably had beene uſed to tilth. And thereby,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Idleneſſe, the ground and begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of all miſchiefs, daily did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe: For, where in ſome Townes, 200 perſons lived by their lawfull la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, they are now occupied, by two or three heard-men.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Husbandry, one of the greateſt commodities of the Realme greatly decaied.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Churches deſtroyed, and the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:1301:21"/>vice of God withdrawne by diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Church living, decay of tithes, and the like.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Patrons and Curats, Gods Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters wronged.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The defence of the land againſt forraigne enemies feebled and impai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            <p>The two conſequences that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of theſe inconveniences, Are,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The diſpleaſure of <hi>Almighty God.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. Subverſion of the policy, and good rule of the land. For remedy whereof it was enacted; that if any owners of houſes of Husbandry, which had beene let to farme, with twenty Acres of land at leaſt, or more lying in tillage and Husbandry; And the occupiers did not maintaine the houſes and buildings convenient for upholding the ſaid tillage; The Lord of the Fee had power to receive year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly halfe the iſſues and profits of the land, untill the houſes were ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly builded or repaired againe. The Statute of 7<hi rend="sup">0</hi>. of HEN. 8. <hi>ca.</hi> 1.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:1301:21"/>was to the ſame purpoſe, not much different, and ſo was the Stature of 27. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>ca.</hi> 22.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>24</label> But theſe acts, and all other ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent acts, as namely, the act of 5. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. by which, ſo much provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence was had for the ſupportation of tillage, as that Commiſſions were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded into ſeverall Counties, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of the offences, and delicts, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted contrary to the tenor of that Stature; And the acts 2. and 3. <hi>Phil.</hi> and <hi>Mar. ca.</hi> 2. by which the Statute of 4. <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. <hi>ca.</hi> 19. was revived and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, and Commiſſions a warded to certaine perſons, to enquire of all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faults and offences committed ſince An. 20. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. or then after to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, contrary to the tenor of the fore-cited Statutes of 4. <hi>H.</hi> 7.19. and 7. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.1. and the act of 5. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 2. which repealed the Statues of 5. and 6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6.5. and 2. and 3. <hi>Phi.</hi> and <hi>Ma.</hi> 2. confirming the reſt, were all repealed 39. <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 1. And thereby explained and enacted, that every
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:1301:22"/>houſe which at that time, or then after, had twenty acres (to bee adjudged ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ordinance, <hi>de terris menſurandis</hi>) of errable land, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe, and paſture, or more, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto belonging, and ſo let to farme for three yeares together, ſince the beginning of the <hi>Queenes</hi> raigne (not being the Caſtle, or dwelling Houſe of any Nobleman, or Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, nor the chiefe manſion houſe of any Mannor) ſhall be adjudged a houſe of husbandry for ever, with many proviſions for repairing, and new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>building houſes of husbandry:<note place="margin">39. <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 2.</note> was ſame Parliament an Act <hi>ca.</hi> 2. was made, that errable land converted to ſheepe paſtures, or to the fatting or grazing of cattell ſince 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> ſhould bee reſtored or laid to tillage, and ſo continue for ever, according to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the ſoile, and courſe of husban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry, with ſome clauſes and reſtrictions, and a penalty of twenty ſhillings for every acre for every yeare not reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. I cannot omit the reaſons of this
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:1301:22"/>Law inforced in the entrance of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That the ſtrength and flouriſhing eſtate of this kingdome hath beene alwayes upheld and advanced by the maintenance of the Plow and tillage.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Tillage is the occaſion of multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying of people, both for ſervice in the wars, and time of peace.</p>
            <p n="3">3 A principall meanes that people are ſet on worke, and thereby with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawne from idleneſſe, drunkenneſſe, unlawfull games, and all other lewd practizes and conditions of life.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That by tillage and husbandry, the greater part of the ſubjects are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved from extreme poverty in a competent eſtate of maintenance and meanes to live.</p>
            <p n="5">5 The wealth of the Realme kept, diſperſed and diſtributed in many hands, where it is more ready to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer all neceſſary charges for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Realme.</p>
            <p n="6">6 It is a cauſe that the Realme doth more ſtand upon it ſelfe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:1301:23"/>out depending upon forreigne Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, either for importation of Corne, in time of ſcarcity, or for vent and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terance of our owne commodities.</p>
            <p>Theſe two laſt mentioned Acts, were but to endure to the end of the next Seſſion of Parliament, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing holden 43. <hi>Eliz.</hi> they were then revived and continued, <hi>ca.</hi> 9. and likewiſe continued 1. <hi>Iacobi.</hi> 25. and afterward diſcontinued, and by the Statute of 21. <hi>Iacob.</hi> all the ſaid other Statutes againſt decay of houſes, were utterly repealed. And ſo the remedy muſt have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the Common Law, and the wiſedome of the State.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>25</label> I thought it no great digreſſion from any purpoſe, ſuccinctly to runne over thoſe Comitiar Lawes, framed according to the neceſſity of the times wherein they were made, that wee may obſerve the opinion, and deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thoſe times had of this exorbitant evill: And though thoſe Lawes be by repeale and expiration exauctorated,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:1301:23"/>yet the inconveniences and miſchiefes pointed out by them, ſtill remaining, and increaſing, and the nature and quality of the offence, tranſcending from meane Tenants to great Land. lords, from ſmall quantities of acres, to whole <hi>Towneſhips, tythings and hamlets;</hi> The care and cure muſt bee greater and ſpeedier, then any Stature-Law hath hitherto provided: Yet there is one Law made 25.<note place="margin">25 <hi>He.</hi> 8. <hi>ca.</hi> 13.</note> 
               <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>ca.</hi> 13. intituled, <hi>An act limiting what number of ſheepe men ſhall keepe, occupie, and have in their owne poſſeſsion at one time,</hi> ſtill in force, and unrepealed, which though in the frontiſpice it ſeemes to looke upon a ſillie company of ſheepe, it doth unkennell a ſubtill ſort of Foxes, which waſte and ſpoile the Vineyard of the Common wealth. Obſerve (1) the footing of theſe Fox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, by their practizes, and injuries to the common good: (2) the miſchiefes, and inconveniences thereupon hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penning: (3) the great conſequence inſuing: (4) the remedy provided by that Law.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:1301:24"/>
1 It diſcovereth unto us, that ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry of the Kings Subjects, to whom GOD had diſpoſed great plenty of moveable ſubſtance, did daily practiſe and invent waies and meanes how they might accumulate and gather together into few hands, as well great multitudes of farmes, as great plenty of Cattell, and in eſpeciall ſheepe, putting ſuch lands as they can get, to paſture, and not to tillage.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The incoveniences foure fold.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That thereby they have pulled downe Churches, and Townes.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Inhaunſed the old rates of the rents of the poſſeſſions of this Realm, or brought it to ſuch exceſſive fines, that no poore man is able to meddle with it.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That they have raiſed the prices of all manner of Corne, Cattel, Wool, and ſuch other, almoſt double above the accuſtomed prices.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That multitudes of people not able to provide neceſſary victualls and cloathing, for themſelves, their wives
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:1301:24"/>and children, were ſo diſcouraged with miſery and poverty, that they fell daily to theft, robbery, and other inconveniences, or pittifully dyed for hunger and cold.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The conſequence or enormities inſuing, five fold.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That things thus uſed be princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally to the high diſpleaſure of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God.</p>
            <p n="2">2 To the decay of the hoſpitality of this Realme.</p>
            <p n="3">3 To the diminiſhing of the Kings people.</p>
            <p n="4">4 To the let of Cloth-making, whereby many poore people had beene accuſtomed to bee ſet to worke.</p>
            <p>If remedy were not found, it might turne to the utter deſtruction and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation of the Realme.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The remedy preſcribed, 2. fold, reſtriction and limitation.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That none ſhould occupie in farme, or otherwiſe have of his owne proper cattell, in his owne proper
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:1301:25"/>lands, nor in the poſſeſſion, lands or grounds of any other, which hee ſhall have in farme, by any manner of meanes, craft, or cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning above two thouſand ſheep at one time, within any part of the Realme, upon paine of three ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings and foure pence for every ſheepe above that number.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That none ſhould take in farme for terme of life, yeares, or at will, any more houſes and renements of husbandry whereunto any lands are belonging, in Towne, Village, Hamlet or tything, above the number of two, upon the penalty of three ſhillings and foure pence for every weeke.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>26</label> All theſe Statutes are but <hi>municipalis aperturae legis,</hi> overtures of the ancient Common Law; One of the maineſt ſpeciall occaſions of this grand miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, is a growing evill of late yeares practized and ſet on foote by certaine greedy and covetous perſons, <hi>Carnifices &amp; carnivoros regni,</hi> grazing
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:1301:25"/>butchers, who under colour of their <hi>mechainck trade</hi> in butchery, reſpecting their owne private gaine and lucre, above the generall good of his Highneſſe Subjects, doe accumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late and gaine into their hands, at ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive yearly rents, ſeverall great portions and parts of the grounds and lands of this Realme, from ſeverall Landlords, and perſons, to the value of foure hundred, five hundred, eight hundred, or a thouſand pounds a yeare, more or leſſe, from the occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of poore husbandmen, to the intent to uſe it in paſture, and not in tillage; and thereby not onely to graze and feede great ſtore of ſheepe, and other Cattell, which they uſually buy in great numbers, to the intent to ſell them alive, contrary to the true meaning of a good Law, made in the third and fourth yeares of the Reigne of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, <hi>cap. xix.</hi> continued by the laſt Parliament, <hi>An.</hi> 3. <hi>Car. Reg. ca.</hi> 4. but alſo to agift, and take to paſture in thoſe ſeveral grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:1301:26"/>the Cattell of diverſe poore husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and others at very high and unuſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all rates and prices; By meanes wherof the poore laborious husbandmen in moſt parts of the Kingdome, whoſe tenements doe moſt conſiſt of errable land, are intercepted and foreſtalled from renting any competent quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of medowe, or paſture to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine their Oxen, and other Cattell, to keepe the plow in uſe according to the ſeaſon of the yeare; And thoſe grounds which within the ſpace of few yeares have beene let at reaſonable yearly rates to neighboring husbandmen, are now by the ſupplantings and outbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of thoſe and ſuch like covetuous accumulators inhaunſed to the full double value; to the great diſcomfort and diſcouragement of the husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who ofttimes is inforced for want of foode and fodder for his Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en and Cattell, to ſell them away, and to leave his grounds untilled.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>27</label> That Devill Covetuoſneſſe the mother of all theſe miſchiefes, hath
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:1301:26"/>ever ſome argument, to elude (if it could) the intention of all Law and Iuſtice; In this caſe it will with a high hand, <hi>umbonibus junctis,</hi> preſſe a double argument by way of queſtion. 1. <hi>a proprio</hi> (2) <hi>ab utili.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>A proprio,</hi> Is it not lawfull for mee to doe what I liſt with my owne, to pull or let down my owne houſes, or alter the property of my owne ſoyle, <hi>&amp;c?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Ab utili,</hi> Shall I not buy and purchaſe as much as I am able to pay for; And ſhall I not make the moſt of my owne?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>28</label> They are generall queſtions, and one generall <hi>maxime</hi> will ſerve to anſwer both, <hi>Intereſt reipublicae, nequis re ſua male utatur;</hi> The intereſt of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale hath ſuch a power over the actions and eſtates of men, that no man muſt abuſe or miſ-imploy the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent of his meanes; And by the rules of contraries, every man muſt well and rightfully order and imploy it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:1301:27"/>
It agrees with the rule of Law and reaſon, <hi>Prohibetur ne quis faciat in ſuo, quod nocere poſsit alieno: Et ſic utere tuo, ut alienum non laedas:</hi> No man muſt do that in his own property or poſſeſſion, as may hurt another mans; And we muſt ſo uſe our owne, that we may not offend our neighbour: This rule may ſeeme to reflect upon particular nuſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to the diſcommodity of <hi>vicinage</hi> and neighborhood, which are to bee remedied by actions at the Common Law, whereof many particular caſes might be plentifully urged: If in ſuch caſes the Law provides a remedy, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra vicinum &amp; privatum nocumentum,</hi> againſt a private annoyance; <hi>à fortiori,</hi> againſt <hi>commune nocumentum,</hi> that nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance which offends many, which the wiſedome of the Law meets with, by Indictments, preſentments, and other wayes in ſeverall Courts of Iuſtice. But <hi>à mulio fortiori,</hi> againſt <hi>generale no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumentum,</hi> that which diſpleaſeth and offendeth not one alone, or many, but <hi>All, God</hi> and <hi>man,</hi> and of men <hi>all</hi> ſorts,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:1301:27"/>from the higheſt to the loweſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>29</label> It is an undoubted Principle, <hi>omne bonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt ſui diffuſivum;</hi> Al goodnes doth communicate it ſelfe to others: he that racketh and tentereth his <hi>bona fortunae,</hi> his fortune, and meanes, to improve his private, and impaire the publike good, hath not participation of this <hi>goodneſſe:</hi> And as little hath hee of that cardinall and all-crowning vertue, <hi>Charity,</hi> the groundſell of religion, without which nothing availeth, <hi>ſine Charitate nihil prodeſt, quia fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum religionis Charitas eſt. Charity,</hi> ſaith <hi>Saint Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. <hi>non quaerit quae ſua ſunt: It ſeeketh not her owne,</hi> it prefers the good of others before its owne private; In a former <hi>Chapter, cap.</hi> 10. <hi>ver.</hi> 24. <hi>Let no man ſeeke his owne, but every man anothers wealth;</hi> The words, either in the literal accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or taken according to the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> meaning, doe inſinuate, that no man muſt ſo uſe his owne, as thereby to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend his neighbour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Non nobis nati ſumus,</hi> wee are not
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:1301:28"/>borne for our ſelves, but partly for our friends, and partly for our Country, It is a vulgar Country proverbe, <hi>every man for himſelfe and God for us all.</hi> But a reverend Divine thus inverted it; Where every man is for himſelfe; <hi>non deus, ſed diabolus,</hi> The Divell is for all: The rich mans barne is full of Corne; It is his owne, <hi>jure proprietatis;</hi> But he muſt not hide and hoard it up to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hance the price, hee muſt expoſe it to publike ſale, and at reaſonable prices, <hi>propter commune bonum,</hi> Or elſe a <hi>vae qui abſcondit</hi> is denounced againſt him: He that received but one Talent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to him by his Lord, wherein he had but a fiduciary intereſt, and hid it, and did not rightly uſe it, was caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to utter darkeneſſe, and had his Talent taken from him: <hi>Matthew</hi> 25.15. we are all but truſtees of this world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſtate or earthly Talent; As wee muſt not hide, but uſe it; So muſt wee uſe it, not for our ſelves onely, but for the common utility of the weale pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:1301:28"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>31</label> As it tranſgreſſeth the bond of <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> the <hi>Crowne</hi> of all good gifts and graces; It doth likewiſe offend againſt the rules of Iuſtice, the <hi>Queene regent</hi> of all vertues; The confeſſion of ſins daily celebrated by the Church, doth conclude by way of prayer, that wee may live a godly, righteous and a ſober life, which implies three duties, piety to God, Iuſt ce or upright dealing to our Neighbour, and ſobriety to our ſelves: I meddle but with the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>32</label> Iuſtice is either univerfall, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a man doth juſtlie carry himſelfe, and levell his actions for the common and publike good, and yeeldeth obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to all lawes, <hi>ut ex earum praeſcripto omnes alias virtutes colat:</hi> That by the rule or preſcript of thoſe lawes, he may have all other vertues in eſteeme, which <hi>Aristotle</hi> calls <hi>legall, quia leges eam praecipue intendunt,</hi> for that the whole uſe and operation of the law is for the ſupport and executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:1301:29"/>
Or it is <hi>particularis,</hi> which is alſo called <hi>Morall,</hi> and is a vertue buſied and exerciſed in the diſtribution and commutation, or merchandizing of all outward things. The object of her imployment and negotiation, <hi>ſunt bona externa, &amp; fortunae, ut opes &amp; honores,</hi> all externall goods, and goods of fortune, as riches, and honours; Hence it is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into diſtributive and Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative Iuſtice.</p>
            <p>This obſerveth an arithmeticall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion in all exchanges, contracts, covenants and commerce, betweene man and man, ſtrictly looking upon the equality of the thing bought, ſold, bartered, or exchanged, without reſpect of the perſon, party in the bargaine, whether he be a Noble man, Citizen, or Plebeian, rendring the price no leſſe unto the one, than to the other; It hath this generall rule to be exerciſed in all entercourſes of buying, ſelling, and dealings whatſoeuer, <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.6. <hi>That no man outreach, or circumvent his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in any matter, ne quis ſupergredia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:1301:29"/>vel circumveniat in negotio fratrem ſuum;</hi> This Iuſtice, the <hi>depopulating queſtioniſts</hi> may in ſome meaſure ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, when they do buye or ſell, they may afford <hi>rem pro pretio, pretium pro re;</hi> But they will not ſell their lands and commodities with conveniencie, either of time or price, till the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Common wealth are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſuffer for want of it: And in buying and accumulating Vineyard to Vineyard, they are ſo exceſſive and outragious, that they become maſters of a whole Countrey, and none muſt have any thing neare them, but at their prices; This kinde of Iuſtice commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative reſpecteth only private perſons; That other <hi>(i.e.)</hi> liſtributive, reſpecteth publike perſons: By the one wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud or doe injury to no man; by the other wee benefit and doe good to all men.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>33</label>
               <hi>Distributive Iustice</hi> hath this inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leble character, <hi>alienum non vendicat, utilitatem propriam negligit. Vt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munem aequitatem cuſtodiat;</hi> She claims
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:1301:30"/>not that which belongs unto another, ſhe paſſeth by her owne profit, that ſhee may preſerve common right; It hath this generall rule, <hi>Galathians</hi> 6.10. <hi>As we have occaſion,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Let us doe good to all men;</hi> Not only individually to any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar perſon or member, but to the King, the head of the State, and to the Church and Common weale, the body, and not at any ſtinted or expectatory times, but upon all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities, <hi>Salutem qui cum poterit, protrahit, negat;</hi> The delaying of ſuccour and reliefe, when a man may afford it, is as much as an abſolute de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall.</p>
            <p>The violating of this Iuſtice, is ever a privative injuſtice, whereby we doe not that common good, as we ought to do; It is aſwell injuſtice (though not alike) not to doe for our brother what we ought, as to doe what wee ought not, according to that ſaying, <hi>paſce eſurientem; ſi non paviſti, occidiſti,</hi> feede thy hungry brother, if thou feed
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:1301:30"/>him not, thou art a homicide priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, if not poſitively. If ſo; In what caſe is the <hi>Depopulator?</hi> He doth not onely not feed the hungry, but rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth them of their bread, and therein he is a man of bloud: <hi>panis pauperum eſt vita pauperum, &amp; qui defraudat, vir ſanguinis eſt:</hi> Nay he is a <hi>matricide,</hi> he choakes up the earth our common mother, from yeelding her foizon and increaſe unto her offspring.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>34</label> It is reported by an ancient Crono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loger, <hi>Walter Mappe</hi> Archdeacon of <hi>Oxford,</hi> who was bred up with <hi>Hen.</hi> 2. That the <hi>Abbots</hi> and, <hi>Monkes</hi> in that time were very criminous in matter of <hi>depopulation,</hi> whence a proverbe did ariſe of them, <hi>Monachi deſertum, aut inveniunt aut faciunt</hi> whereſoever they ſetled themſelues, they either <hi>found</hi> it, or <hi>made it a deſart:</hi> It is ſaid of them, that they laid more places waſte, then ever <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror, or his Son <hi>Rufus</hi> did, when they demoliſhed and deſtroyed many pariſhes with their <hi>Churches</hi> to inlarge the bounds of New forreſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:1301:31"/>
The <hi>Abbot</hi> of <hi>Oſney,</hi> was principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly noted for a great <hi>Depopulator;</hi> he made all poore that dwelt within the compaſſe of his poſſeſſions; whereof King <hi>Hen.</hi> 2. tooke ſuch notice, that one day, when hee had not poore e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, to beſtow his almes unto, upon ſome feſtivall and ſolemne time did diſcontentedly affirme, that rather then his bounty ſhould be undiſpoſed, hee would make as many beggers, as the <hi>Abbot</hi> of <hi>Oſney</hi> had done.</p>
            <p>Their <hi>monaſteries</hi> and <hi>religious</hi> houſes were no ſooner diſſolved, but eftſoones their goodly ſtructures were waſted and ruined, yet their lands (as if they ſeemed to carry with them a ſucceſſorie adherence of this leproſie) have fallen into the hands of many more uncharitable then ever they were; for as they made poore, they did in ſome competencie maintaine and releeve them; But theſe doe not only make many poore, but ſtarve thoſe that are poore.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>35</label> It was the Law of GOD by the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:1301:31"/>mouth of <hi>Moſes,</hi> Lev. 19.9. <hi>When you reape the harveſt of your land, thou ſhalt not wholly reape the corners of the field, neither ſhalt thou gather the gleanings of thy harveſt.</hi> Verſe 10. <hi>And thou ſhalt not gleane the Vineyard, neither ſhalt thou ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther every grape of thy Vineyard: thou ſhalt leave them for the poore and ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger:</hi> The like, Ch. 23. Ver. 22. <hi>Thou ſhalt not make cleane riddance of the corners of thy field, when thou reapeſt, neither ſhalt thou gather any gleanings of thy harveſt: thou ſhalt leave them unto the poore, and to the ſtranger: Hee that had forgotten a ſheafe behind him in the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt, ſhould not goe againe to fetch it, but leave it behind for the ſtranger, the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe, and the widdow, Deut.</hi> 24.19.</p>
            <p>A bleſſing is promiſed, that the LORD thy GOD may bleſſe thee in all the workes of thy hands; then needs muſt bee implyed, whoſoever doth it not, ſhall not be bleſſed; where benedictions are excluded, woes and maledictions ſoone make their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance, where there is no tillage, there
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:1301:32"/>can bee no harveſt, and where no harveſt is, no reliques, no gleanings can be.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Deeſt cultura? labant meſſes, &amp; meſſe labanti.</l>
               <l>Deficient inopi, ſpicas, frumenta le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genti.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>If tillage faile, the harveſts faile, which once failing,</l>
               <l>The corne cannot yeeld unto the poore their gleaning.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Woe then to the <hi>Depopulator,</hi> who is ſo farre from making riddance of the corners of the fields, that he rids whole fields, and takes away all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of gleanings and harveſt, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barring and forechoaking the worke of tillage, by converting errable into paſture, and ruinating the habitations of husbandry, by turning them into ſheep-coates; Our times cannot make good that ſaying, <hi>Nunc ſeges eſt ubi Troj a fuit:</hi> Now corne growes where houſes ſtood; but we may take it up with a lamentation; where hoſpitable
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:1301:32"/>Farmes, and plentifull fields of corne have beene, nothing remaines but a champant wilderneſſe for ſheepe, with a Coate, a paſtorall boy, his dogge, a crooke and a pipe.</p>
            <q>In caſulas, veteres manſus mutantur oviles.</q>
            <p>Or as the <hi>Thebans</hi> in the time of a devouring peſtilence, bewailed the loſſe of their husbandmen.</p>
            <q>— Viduas colonis Reſpicis terras miſeranda Thebe:<note place="margin">Senec. tra. in Oedip.</note>
            </q>
            <p>Wee might in theſe contagious dayes of <hi>depopulation,</hi> juſtly expect the like querimony, if his Majeſties gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, and watchfull providence, in preventing ſuch miſchiefs, did not cheere up our fainting hearts.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>36</label> One of the inſtruments of <hi>depopula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is incloſure, I doe not meane of waſts, woods and paſtures, ſo farre as they are warranted by ſeverall Lawes and Statutes; for where a man hath Common in the Lords waſt ground,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:1301:33"/>the Lord by the Law may incloſe part of the waſte for himſelfe, leaving ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe ſufficient Common with egreſſe and regreſſe for the Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: And it is called approvement <hi>(appruamentum)</hi> that is, to make the beſt benefit thereof by increaſing the rent; And if the Lord doth approve his waſte, not leaving ſufficient Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon for the Tenants, the Law gives them a remedy againſt the Lord by writ of aſſize: But my ayme is at in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſing of common fields uſed to cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and converting them into paſture, whereby one grand offence and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience not yet formerly mentioned doth ariſe: The ſtopping and ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Kings high wayes: For whereas by the Statute of <hi>Winton,</hi> 13. <hi>Edw.</hi> 1.5. It was commanded that high wayes leading from one Market Towne to another, ſhould be inlarged, where buſhes, woods, or dykes were, ſo that there ſhould be neither dyke, tree nor buſh, whereby a man might lurke to doe hurt, within two hundred
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:1301:33"/>foote of the one ſide, and two hundred foote of the other ſide of the way, (except Aſhes or great Trees) By the meaning of which Law, the Kings high waies (which the Common Law had ever in high eſtimation) were to be of ſuch ſufficient breadth, that three or foure Carts or carriages might well paſſe in range together, without any ſtop or impediment: Now in moſt parts of the Kingdome, within the ſpace of theſe forty yeares, There have beene ſo much Circumſeption and wounding in of common errable lands and fields, abutting and adjoyning to high waies, by Tenants with conſent of the Lord of the fee (all partakers of the crime) and the high waies thereby ſo ſtreightned, that in many places, but one Cart, and not without ſome dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and difficulty, can paſſe, and ſcarce two horſemen ſide by ſide, without climing upon ſide bankes, whence theſe inconveniences and miſchiefes muſt needs ariſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1 A great danger to his Majeſties
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:1301:34"/>Subjects in being expoſed to aſſaſſina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and robberies, with little poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility to avoide or reſiſt them, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the narrowneſſe and incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the wayes.</p>
            <p n="2">2 As great a danger to his highneſſe leige people, who upon neceſſitated oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, either for his highneſſe publik ſervice, or for common entercourſe and trafficke, being upon the height of ſpeed (which brooks no delaie) <hi>Omnis nimium long a properanti mora eſt,</hi> doe oftentimes in ſtreight and narrow lanes (I cannot terme them waies, for the way aſwel as the word are become diminutives, <hi>via</hi> is turned into <hi>viculi</hi>) meete with countercourſes and are ready for want of competent ſpatiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which might decline the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine diſtreſſe, raſhly encounter each other, to the perill of their limbes or lives.</p>
            <p n="3">3 A manifeſt impairment or po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulation of the waies themſelves doth this ſtraightneſſe produce, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by not onely makes them unpaſſable
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:1301:34"/>upon ſome unſeaſonable times &amp; wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to the great trouble and impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Subjects, who are infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to compaſſe their journey with much tediouſneſſe, through private grounds, and other by-wayes; But it doth alſo exhauſt from the poore neighbouring Inhabitants, a farre greater and more frequent charge of reparations, then if they had the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute allowance of latitude; the often preſſures and treadings in one tract, wil ſooner founder a way, then if there were variety and choice of tracts which would be ſupplied in breadth according to that law of <hi>Winton,</hi> if in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſures were not in the way.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>37</label>
               <hi>All the miſchiefs and miſerable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences before cited, I ſhall reduce in one diſtick.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Rex patitur, patitur clerus, reſpub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica, pauper;</l>
               <l>Et non paſſurus depopulator erit?</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:1301:35"/>
               <hi>Rex patitur:</hi> The King ſuffers; 1 Firſt in his Royall Majeſtie, he cannot number ſo many ſtrong and able men as he might doe, if tillage had its ancient eſteeme: In the multitude of people <hi>is the Kings honour, but in the want of people is the deſtruction of the Prince: In pautitate plebis ignominia Principis, Prov.</hi> 14.28. It was the lamentation of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> Lamen. 1.1. <hi>How doth the City ſit ſolitary, that was full of people? how is ſhee become as a widow?</hi> Amongſt people the husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are noted to be <hi>homines ſtrenuiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi,</hi> the ſtrongeſt men, and fitteſt for any labour, whence <hi>Seneca</hi> obſerved; <hi>Nullum laborem recuſant manus quae ab aratro ad arma transferuntur:</hi> Their hands refuſe no labour, who from the exerciſe of the Plow are trayned to the field; The Law therefore of 39. <hi>Eliz. ca.</hi> 1. doth excellently ſet forth; That the ſtrength and flouriſhing eſtate of this Kingdome hath beene alwaies up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held and advanced by tillage, and people thereby multiplied for ſervice,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:1301:35"/>both in times of war and peace, and by the decay of it, the defence of the land, againſt forreigne enemies have been feebled and decayed.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Secondly in the meanes and maintenance of his imperiall ſtate, and therefore a <hi>depopulator</hi> may bee well called <hi>depeculator,</hi> a robber of the Kings treaſury: for it muſt of neceſſity be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhed and farre ſhortned, if ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Families (who were able to pay ſubſidies, fifteenes, and other duties to ſupply the KINGS neceſſities, aſwell for the ſupport of his regali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as for the defence of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome) bee utterly decayed and diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled: And it is a common practice with Landlords and others, to keepe tenements in their hands, and inſteed of Subſidies, to pay the King with Certificates. It is the prudent policy of a Prince, in the time of peace to make proviſion for the maintenance of warre, <hi>Nulla quies gentium ſine armis,</hi> the peace of a Nation cannot be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an army; No armies without
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:1301:36"/>Souldiers, no Souldiers without ſala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, no ſalaries without tributes and taxes to the <hi>Prince.</hi> And where there are no people, there can be no paime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, and then the deſolation of a Kingdom muſt needs follow, which I hope our Nation ſhall never ſee.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>38</label>
               <hi>Patitur Clerus:</hi> The <hi>Church</hi> ſuffers, 1. in the decay and ruine of materiall temples, oratories, chappels and houſes of religion, 2. abating and diminiſhing the number of painefull and learned <hi>Paſtors,</hi> 3. in robbing God and his holy Church of tythes both perſonall and prediall: for where Towns, Pariſhes, and Villages are diſpeopled, there muſt be a failing of perſonall duties: And where errable lands are converted into paſture, there muſt needs inſue a dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution of predial tythes: ſheep do never yeeld ſo much profit and advantage to Gods Miniſters, as the ſheafe; this is commonly ſure to be paid in kind: In the tything of the other, which conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in wooll and lambe, there are many ſlights and ſubtil deceipts of late crept
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:1301:36"/>in, and many devices ſtarted up by co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous and ill diſpoſed perſons; They will either ſhift away their ſheepe from one place to another; and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times upon a petty compoſition with a neighbour incumbent from one pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh to another, and ſo incumber the tything for the fall of Lambes, and ſet a variance betweene the Miniſters, or they will ſell their ſheep a little before the time of ſhearing, and ſo cheat the Miniſter of his dues in the title of wooll; And to countenance this pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, ſome ſtrange preſcription, or <hi>modus decimandi</hi> muſt preſently be ſet on foot, a prohibition ſpeedily had, and the litigious Countrymans next labour is, to provide for a tryall at the aſſizes, and to prepare (as the too com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon proverbe is, <hi>horreſco referens</hi>) good ſwearers, that may cleave a pinne, and ſo by horrid perjury out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrip God and his Miniſters of their juſt dues; It is lamentable to ſee what perplexed ſwearing and counterſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing do often happen upon ſuch tryalls.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:1301:37"/>
               <hi>Qui rem Sacram legit;</hi> He that robs Churches, or Chappels, or other holy places, and takes any ornaments out of them feloniouſly, is to ſuffer death by the Law, without benefit of Clergy: I will not terme the <hi>Depopulator Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legus:</hi> Sacred things which are ſtollen a way, may be poſſibly found and had againe; But I ſhall call him <hi>ſacrivorus,</hi> ſuch a devouring <hi>Leviathan,</hi> that ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes Steeples, Churches, and whole fields, and makes a <hi>non entitie,</hi> and takes away the very being of ſacred things appoynted and deſigned for the glory of God, and the maintenance of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: Hee adnuls that ſacred rule, <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour God with thy ſubſtance, and with the firſt fruits of all thine increaſe: Pro.</hi> 2.9. The Prophet brandeth ſuch men with a juſt accuſation of robbery, <hi>will a man rob God? yet yee have robbed mee: But ye ſay wherein have we robbed thee? in tithes and offerings: ye are curſed with a curſe, for yee have robbed mee, Malac.</hi> 3.8. Therefore juſt was the complaint of the Parliament, 4 <hi>He.</hi> 7. <hi>ca.</hi> 19. That
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:1301:37"/>Churches were deſtroyed, and the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God withdrawne by diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Church living, decay of tithes, and the like; and Patrons of Churches, and Curats, <hi>Gods</hi> Miniſters were wronged.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Patitur reſpublica.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>39</label> In whatſoever the King doth ſuffer, the Publike-weale hath a ſhare; if the Head be grieved, the whole Body will ſympathize: <hi>The Common-Weale of England, is a Society or common doing of Freemen, collected together, and united by common accord,</hi> and governed by the adminiſtation of lawes, as well in peace as in warre, under the Princely rule and protection of an abſolute Monarch, who, under God, is ſupreme head both of Church and State, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth no other <hi>Superiour.</hi> It is called the <hi>Common-weale, quia reſpicit communem utilitatem,</hi> becauſe it reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth the common good: The <hi>Depopu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lator</hi> ſtrikes at the verie ſtructure and frame of a <hi>Common-weale,</hi> by diſpeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pling of Societies in Townes, Pariſhes,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:1301:38"/>and Hamlets. He brings in Idleneſſe, the ground and foundation of all miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes, accompanied with luxury, ebrietie, unlawfull games, and all other lewd practices and conditions of life: He is the common inhanſer of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes of all manner of Corne, Graine, and Victuall, and of all the old rents of ancient Farmes and Poſſeſſions: Hee makes the kingdome beholding to forraigne Countries for importation of Corne in times of ſcarcitie. By his unconſcionable incloſures the Kings high wayes are ſtreightned and impai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and commonly foundred, to the hinderance and impediment of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon mercature, and travaile to and fro: There is not one good qualitie in him for the common good.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>40</label>
               <hi>Patitur pauper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The poore ſuffers: for whereas by tillage and husbandrie the greater part of the ſubjects are preſerved from ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme povertie in a competent eſtate of maintenance, and meanes to live; now by the decay of it multitudes of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:1301:38"/>not able to provide neceſſarie vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuals and cloathing for themſelves, and their families, are ſo diſcouraged with miſerie and povertie, that they daily fall to theft, robberie, and other inconveniences, and either die by the hand of Iuſtice, or periſh and ſtarve in a Gaole. It is woefull to ſee, that thoſe places are now more peſtered with poore priſoners, than heretofore they were. As it doth depauperate able men, ſo, for want of almes and glea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, it is a meanes to ſtarve and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh them, when they are made poore; for the poore labourer, who, like the painfull <hi>Ant,</hi> was wont in harveſt time to glean, and leaſe up ſo much corne, as would thriftily maintaine him a good part of the winter, is now for want of tillage, deſtituted of that benefit.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>41</label> But now (God and the wiſdome of our great Soveraigne by him inſpired, be bleſſed) <hi>Paſſurus eſt depopulator,</hi> you have heard him diſcovered, deſcribed, arraigned, &amp; convicted, &amp; ere long you ſhall heare his ſentence: His crime is no
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:1301:39"/>leſſe than <hi>crimen laeſae majeſtatis,</hi> high Treaſon againſt the ſacred Trinity of heaven, in compaſſing about the viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting &amp; cancelling of that great Charter, or, <hi>magna Charta</hi> of <hi>terram dedit filiis hominum, ut operarentur;</hi> and indeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to overthrow Gods inſtitution of husbandrie, <hi>primum opus impoſitum;</hi> and in ſtead of <hi>operari,</hi> to bring in <hi>otiari,</hi> in ſtead of many labourers in the harveſt, to maintaine onely a ſhepheard and his Curre.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>42</label> The Charter of confirmation of the liberties of <hi>England,</hi> and the forreſts, made 10. <hi>Octo.</hi> 25. <hi>Edw.</hi> 1.1297. doth provide <hi>cap.</hi> 4. that all Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and Biſhops, ſhould pronounce the ſentence of excommunication a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all thoſe that by word, deed or counſell, doe contrary to the ſaid Charters, or that in any point breake or undoe them: and that the ſaid Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſhould be twice a yeare denounced, and publiſhed by the Prelats aforeſaid. The ſentence of excommunication is extant, ſtiled <hi>ſententia lata ſuper confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matione
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:1301:39"/>Chartarum;</hi> whereby <hi>Robert Wincheſly</hi> then Archbiſhop of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> did excomunicate all the violaters of thoſe Charters, <hi>from the body of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, from all the company of heaven, and from all the Sacraments of holy Church for ever, fiat, fiat, Amen.</hi> Though neither the Anathema of that time, being now expired, nor any of this time doe meet with them; yet let them expect, (my charity interdicts the word Curſe) but little bleſſing from heaven. Sure I am, the ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture pronounceth many a <hi>Vae,</hi> many woes againſt the ſeverall qualities and ſpecies of that grand offence: One they have heard already, a <hi>Vae qui ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcondit, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>43</label> A covetous man is deſcribed, that his eye is neither ſatisfied with riches, neither ſaith he, <hi>For whom doe I labour, and bereave my ſoule of good? Eccle.</hi> 4.8. and preſently followes <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. a <hi>Vae ſoli, woe to him that is alene.</hi> The <hi>Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulator</hi> may take up this woe, who will be <hi>alone</hi> in his habitation, without the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:1301:40"/>comfort of neighberhood; <hi>alone</hi> in his actions, without any participation with other; and he ſhall bee <hi>alone</hi> in his pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment: <hi>Vae ſoli,</hi> Woe to him that is <hi>alone</hi> when he falleth; for hee hath not another to helpe him. He that offends all generally, may have the prayers of many to convert him, but ſcarce the prayers of any to helpe him, <hi>Solitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem faciunt, &amp; habent,</hi> ſhall be the Mot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to of ſuch perſons, <hi>Qui neminem miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur, à nemine miſerebitur;</hi> He that pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth none, ſhall bee pittied of none. There is a <hi>Vae qui conjungitis domum ad domum;</hi> Iſai. 5.8. <hi>Wo unto them, that joyne houſe to houſe, that lay field to field, till there bee no place, that they may bee placed in the midſt of the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Prophet <hi>Micha, cap.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. doth ſecond this woe with a <hi>Vae qui co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitatis inutile, &amp; operamini malum, &amp;c. Woe to them that deviſe iniquitie, and worke evill upon their beds, when the morning is light they practiſe it, becauſe it is in the power of their hands. Verſ.</hi> 2. <hi>And that covet fields, and take them by
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:1301:40"/>violence; and houſes, and take them away.</hi> So they oppreſſe a man and his houſe, even a man and his heritage: Their doome followes pronounced by the Prophet: <hi>Idcirco hoc dicit Dominus, ver.</hi> 3. <hi>Therefore thus ſaith the Lord,</hi> with an <hi>ecce, Behold, againſt this family doe I deviſe an evill, from which you ſhall not remove your necks, nether ſhall yee goe haughtily; for this time is evill.</hi> 4. <hi>In that day one ſhall take up a parable againſt you, and lament with a dolefull lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſay</hi> (in the words of S. <hi>Ieromes</hi> tranſlation, <hi>Depopulatione vaſtati ſumus</hi>) <hi>Wee beutterly ſpoyled: He hath changed the portion of my people: how hath hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved it from me? turning away</hi> (or in ſtead of reſtoring) <hi>hee hath divided our fields.</hi> This woe was pronounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and as well againſt their Princes (their mightie men) as againſt the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, for a memoriall and example to all the poſterity of <hi>Adam.</hi> It is remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and ſhould take very much to obſerve the Analogie and proportion
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:1301:41"/>betweene the ſinne and the ſentence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>44</label> In the <hi>ſinne</hi> there is a <hi>deviſing</hi> of an iniquity, a working, of an evill, <hi>malum culpae,</hi> they think upon the evill of ſinne, <hi>Vae qui cogitatis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this <hi>ſentence</hi> there is a <hi>cogito,</hi> a <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing</hi> of an evill too againſt the ſinner, but it is <hi>malum poenae, God</hi> againſt them thinketh upon the evill of puniſhment. In the <hi>ſinne,</hi> there is an <hi>extenſion</hi> conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable in the perſons againſt whom the evill is deviſed and wrought; it is not againſt a man and a field, but <hi>agros</hi> and <hi>domos,</hi> fields and whole houſes, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, men, women, and Children; not gray haires, not men of ſtrength, not the nurſing mother, nor the tender babe; not the very <hi>embrion</hi> in the wombe were exempted from this oppreſſion.</p>
            <p>Vnder the Law the <hi>Dam</hi> was not to be taken with her young ones, <hi>And therefore if a birds neſt chanced to bee found, whether they were young ones or Egges; and the Dam ſitting upon the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:1301:41"/>young, or upon the Egs;</hi> The Precept was, <hi>Thou ſhalt not take the Dam with the young; Deut.</hi> 22. <hi>v.</hi> 6. If God had ſuch care of the fowles of the aire, which was <hi>typicall,</hi> what ſhall bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected amongſt Chriſtians, to whom the Vaile of the Law is opened; <hi>woe</hi> bee to him that ſhall oppreſſe the <hi>Dam</hi> with her young ones.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>ſentence</hi> there is an extent of the evill of puniſhment deviſed, quadrant to the ſinne; <hi>Cogito ſuper iſtam familiam,</hi> Againſt that family doe I deviſe an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill; As if hee ſhould ſay, Againſt the old and ſtrong, the Dam, and her young ones, this evill ſhall cleave to all; <hi>In quo quis peccat, in eo punietur;</hi> I will adde a <hi>qualiter,</hi> and a <hi>taliter;</hi> in that kinde as a man offends, he ſhall bee pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed; he that waſteth and deſtroyeth families, ſhall bee deſtroyed in his families.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>45</label> In the ſinne there is a double effect proceeding from this device and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of evill; 1. Of force or violence, <hi>violenter tulerunt agros, &amp; rapuerunt do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos,</hi>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:1301:42"/>They take away fields and houſes by violence. 2. Of fraud and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, <hi>Calumniabantur virum &amp; do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum ejus, virum &amp; haereditatem ejus;</hi> They oppreſſe a man and his houſe, a man and his heritage, or poſterity. Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion is ever attended with two bad <hi>Angels,</hi> Force and Fraud. In this place the word <hi>calumniabantur</hi> may be taken for oppreſſing a man, his houſe and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritage, by ſome malicious, deceitfull, or crafty allegation and cavill.</p>
            <p>It was the oppreſſing ſinne of <hi>Ahab,</hi> who firſt coveted <hi>Naboths</hi> field, and when he could not get it by a ſpecious pretext of compoſition with him, then with the wicked art and aſſiſtance of <hi>Ieſabel,</hi> an inſtrument of bloud is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived, two children of <hi>Belial</hi> are raiſed up againſt him, <hi>Calumniantur viru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam, &amp; haereditatem,</hi> By falſe and deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full accuſation they robbe him both of life and land.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>46</label> The ſentence meets with both. 1. The force or violence is paid in its kinde with a <hi>malum unde non auferetis colla
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:1301:42"/>veſtra, non ambulabitis ſuperbi:</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, Such an evill will I deviſe, I will ſo ſubdue you, that you ſhall not pull your necks out of the collar; I will ſo curbe you, that ye ſhal have no more power to oppreſſe, yee ſhall walke no more ſo proudly as yee have done. <hi>I will binde your Princes with chaines, and your Nobles with links of iron.</hi> In a word, God threatens to them a miſerable and ſhamefull end. 2. The fraud or falſe circumvention is likewiſe met with, &amp; the puniſhment amplified by a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbe or forme of execration or cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, <hi>calumniabantur,</hi> is anſwered with a <hi>Sumetur ſuper vos parabola,</hi> A parable ſhall bee taken up againſt you, <hi>Wee are ſpoiled,</hi> your cruelty ſhall be recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with perpetuall ignominy. No leſſe judgement did God himſelf denounce by the mouth of his Prophet agianſt the Princes of <hi>Iudah,</hi> &amp; others, That they ſhould be a reproach &amp; <hi>a proverbe, a taunt, and a curſe in all places, in oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brium, &amp; in parabolam, &amp; in proverbium, &amp; in maledictionem in univerſis locis:
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:1301:43"/>Ierem.</hi> 24.9. Amongſt all the curſes pronounced againſt the children of diſobedience, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. from <hi>verſe</hi> 15. unto 45. one of the laſt, and not the leaſt, is a curſe of reproach or infamie; <hi>Eris perditus in proverbium ac fabulam omnibus populis, Thou ſhalt become an aſtoniſhment, a proverbe, and a by-word among all nations. verſe</hi> 37.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>47</label> Let us looke upon the times wherein we live, and behold the ſame ſinne, we ſhall finde a deviſing of an <hi>evill,</hi> cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of fields, joyning houſe to houſe, laying field to field, taking by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and oppreſſing men, and their houſes, and their heritages; and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever can bee compriſed under the word <hi>depopulation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shall not the authors of this <hi>evill,</hi> the <hi>Nimrods,</hi> and migty ones expect the ſame <hi>ſentence,</hi> the ſame puniſhment of evill; the ſame reproach, parable, and proverbe of <hi>Depopulatione vaſtati ſumus?</hi> Yes verily: They will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps flatter themſelves, that the curſes were never intended to this nation; if it
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:1301:43"/>were, yet it is far off, not imminent; and they have time enough to expiate their errour: (they will not confeſſe it a ſinne) They will pretend, that though they build not Churches or Chappels, yet they maintaine a ſtipen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary Preacher in their houſes; and though they are alone, and remote from Churches, yet they are duly fed with the word of God, and they themſelves doe feed the poore too at the times of Chriſtmas, and ſuch ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne times: Theſe are but ſhadowes, and poore palliations. They muſt know, that the curſes of ſacred Writ will one day or another cleave unto them, their houſes, their families and poſterities, without true repentance, ſatisfaction, and reſtitution; and they muſt know it is not a light errour, but as the <hi>Poet</hi> hath it,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sape error ingens ſceleris obtinuit lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a ſtupendious error, and hath ever equivalence with a hainous crime: They muſt not thinke, that
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:1301:44"/>ſuch a grand tranſgreſſion againſt the <hi>Majeſtie</hi> of Heaven, his pious and prudent Vicegerent here on earth, againſt the Church, the State and poore, can bee expiated by a Parlor ſermon of a ſtipendary Schoolma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, who muſt ſow <hi>downe</hi> under his <hi>Patrons</hi> Elbowes; <hi>Vlcus eſt, ne tangas,</hi> he muſt not touch this <hi>maladie,</hi> for feare he ſhould loſe his Salarie; no, nor with their pettie almes at ſtinted times of ſolemne feſtivities, when eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mans hands are open the give, <hi>Ad aliud remedium recurrendum eſt;</hi> They muſt reſort to other Phyſitians, true penitence, and her two companions mentioned before.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>48</label> Their offence is grievous, and ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravated by the example. It is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable, that <hi>omne grave &amp; graſſans ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum aliquem ſemper in populo principem habet;</hi> There is not any great and growing <hi>evill,</hi> but hath ever ſome Prince (I meane ſome great man) to be an example, a patron, and protector of it. If a meane man bee like to bee
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:1301:44"/>queſtioned for ruinating a houſe of husbandry, or tranſlating culture into paſture; he is readie preſently to ſtop the mouth of authority with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probration of his great Ring-leader &amp; Preſident; You (ſaith he) can look upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, &amp; upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my petty ſlips, why ſhould not I for my own private profit &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage do this, as well as ſuch as have no need, and yet ſuffer many houſes together to decay, not habitable nor hoſpitable, naming, and meaning their great <hi>Princes,</hi> and <hi>Patternes</hi> of this <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill?</hi> So that this great one, either by parity in authority, or by alliance in bloud, affinitie, or ſome other reſpects, is ſo neare upon the eye of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey Iuſtice, that the object common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hinders the ſight, and becauſe the greater cannot, the leſſer muſt not bee ſeene: The greater breake the Net, and hold off ordinary power, &amp; ſo all ſcape together <hi>impunè,</hi> if it were not for Superiour Iuriſdiction.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>49</label> I ſpeake it knowingly, &amp; doe appeale to the whole Kingdome. How many
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:1301:45"/>carefull dictates, and remembrances have beene yearely delivered by the right honourable Lord Keeper, from the mouth of his ſacred Majeſtie, in the greateſt threſhing floore of our Nation, to the Reverend Iudges and others, before their addreſſe unto their ſeverall Circuits; requiring them to take ſpeciall notice and inquiry of this grand <hi>evill?</hi> And in purſuance thereof, how earneſt and ſollicitous have thoſe noble Iuſticiaries beene in their charges, and directions to the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of the Peace, and the body of the county, the grand Iurie, ſtrictly to inquire after, and preſent thoſe offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? was there ever any preſentment or indictment effectually proſecuted againſt them, without w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> the judges could work little reformation? Might not the ſingle-hearted eye of one bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy behold a <hi>depopulator</hi> upon the Bench, when the many eyes of that County body, either for feare, favor, ſelf-guiltineſſe, or other by-reſpects, or neglects, did over-looke him?
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:1301:45"/>The meaneſt Country capacity in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very County underſtands what I meane, and therefore I repreſſe my ſelfe from preſſing this point any farther upon the Country, leſt I be ſhent from my labour,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>50</label> Yet <hi>paſſurus eſt Depopulator;</hi> He muſt ſuffer in this world by the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall ſtroke of Iuſtice; for where in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior Courts leave him, Superior finde him: I have before touched up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>diſtributive Iuſtice,</hi> and her oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite <hi>privative injuſtice:</hi> The <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers</hi> divide <hi>diſtributive juſtice</hi> into <hi>remunerative</hi> and <hi>punitive;</hi> This kind of Iuſtice obſerveth a <hi>geometrical pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion;</hi> It doth not barely and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely regard the equality of things, as <hi>Iuſtice co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mutative</hi> doth <hi>rei ad rem, ut tantum quis reponat quantum accipit,</hi> that is to depoſite to all perſons alike in commerce, the price for the thing, and the thing for the price, but ſhee keepeth her equality, according to the diverſities of circumſtances, and the differences of perſons to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:1301:46"/>warded or puniſhed. In wars more reward is to be given to a Captaine in reſpect of the truſt and weighty care of his place, and the dignity of his perſon, then to a common Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier; And if he offend, he muſt looke for a proportionable puniſhment, according to the circumſtances of his offence, and the quality of his perſon and place.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Omne animi vitium, tanto conſpectius in ſe</l>
               <l>Crimen habet, quanto major, qui pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat, habetur.</l>
            </q>
            <p>As the example of an offence in a man of eminence and truſt in the Common wealth, doth not onely ſcandalize the government of a State, but miniſters an occaſion of liberty to others of meaner ranke, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the like or worſe, who are ever moſt prone and forward to run with a multitude, ſoothing themſelves w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> a vaine and falſe opinion, that <hi>multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo errantiam parit errori patrocinium;</hi> So the puniſhment of ſuch a perſon
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:1301:46"/>muſt bee in all things exemplarily proportionable.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>51</label> Some would have <hi>jus talionis</hi> to be part of this Iuſtice: <hi>Ius talionis</hi> is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>ſimplex</hi> or <hi>proportionale;</hi> It is ſimply taken, when the ſame or the like is rendred as was taken away, <hi>an eye for an eye, and a tooth for a tooth;</hi> Taken the other way, it is <hi>compenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio bonorum &amp; malorum facta propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionaliter,</hi> a proportionable compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of good and evill, and is moſt neceſſary in every Chriſtian com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale; This compenſative part of <hi>diſtributive Iuſtice</hi> (without far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſtinctions, I will give it that appellation) hath beene conſtantly practiſed for many ages in this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Iland.</p>
            <p>According to the rule of this <hi>juſtice</hi> was that <hi>conſtitution</hi> of <hi>Fredr. Caeſar</hi> before remembred, made for the protection and vindication of hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry, which limits a quadruple re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the things taken away, for the comfort and compenſation of
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:1301:47"/>the party greeved; And for ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Law againſt the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, <hi>nigro carbone notatur,</hi> he is bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with infany <hi>ipſo jure</hi> in the place of a <hi>vae</hi> ſo often pronounced by the Prophets, and in ſteed or reſemblance of the Parable and Proverbe, threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Law in <hi>Deuteronomie,</hi> and denounced by <hi>Ieremy,</hi> and <hi>Mich.</hi> And hee is to undergoe an arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cenſure at the will of the <hi>Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror.</hi> According to this Iuſtice the Lords and others in the high Court of Starchamber, have ever uſed to proceed, and ground their ſentences againſt delinquents of this and the like nature.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>52</label> In <hi>Michelmas</hi> terme 10. <hi>Car.</hi> Vpon an information exhibited by his Majeſties Attourney generall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a gentleman of note and worth for <hi>Depopulation,</hi> converting great quantities of land into paſture, which formerly for the ſpace of about for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty yeares had beene arrable, uſed to tillage, and occupied as belonging to
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:1301:47"/>ſeverall farme houſes or houſes of husbandry, and ſuffering the farme houſes with their outhouſes to bee ruined and uninhabited, and a water-griſt Mill to decaie and goe to ruine, for that it appeared to the Court up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on evident proofe, that there were many ſervants and people kept upon thoſe farmes when they were uſed in tillage; And the ſame were furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with ſufficient houſes, barnes, and outhouſes, neceſſary for farmers to dwell in, and many quarters of wheat and other graine out of each farme, were yearly ſold and vented to London and elſewhere; And ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny poore men and women, were then there ſet on worke, and about twenty perſons fit for warres were maintained in and upon the ſayd farmes, as alſo ſeverall Carts, ready and fit to doe his Majeſty ſervice, both in carrying timber for repaire of his Navie and otherwiſe: And for that the defendant had then of late yeares, taken into his owne occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:1301:48"/>all the ſaid farmes, and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all the lands formerly uſed for tillage unto paſture, and had alſo <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>populated</hi> and pulled downe, three of the ſaid farme houſes, and ſuffered the other two to run to ruine, and to lye uninhabited, and one of the ſaid farmes which was before a great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and ſuccour for Travellers who paſſed that way, ſince the <hi>Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulation</hi> thereof, hath beene a har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for theeves, and many robbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries have beene thereabouts commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and monies recovered by the robbed perſons from the hundred, which together with the wants of thoſe clowes there formerly kept, had beene a great burden to that part of the Country; And for that alſo the defendant, to the great inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience and prejudice of a Towne neere adjoyning, had pulled downe and ſuffered to goe to decay not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitable, one water corne mill which thentofore did grind good ſtore of corne weekely: Vpon grave and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberate
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:1301:48"/>liberate conſideration, the Court did with a joynt conſent and opinion de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that the defendant was clearly guilty of the ſaid <hi>Depopulation,</hi> and converſion of errable into paſture be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore expreſſed, And that the ſame of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences were puniſhable even by the Common Law of this Kingdome, and fit to be ſeverely puniſhed, the rather for that it was a growing evill, and had already ſpread it ſelfe into very many parts of this Kingdome, and might in time (if it were not met withall and prevented by the juſt Cenſure of that Court) grow very prejudiciall and dangerous to the State and Common wealth, and therefore their Lordſhips did thinke fit, order, adjudge, and decree.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 That the defendant ſhould ſtand and be committed to the priſon of the Fleet.</item>
               <item>2 That hee ſhould pay a fine of foure thouſand pounds to his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties uſe.</item>
               <item>3 That he ſhould at the next aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſizes
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:1301:49"/>to be holden for that County in open Court (the Iudges and Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces there ſitting) acknowledge his ſaid offences, and for the better ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of the offence to the Countrey, and to the end that others ſeeing his puniſhment might be ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by after warned to forbeare the committing of the like: It was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, that their Lordſhips ſentence and decree ſhould be then at the ſaid aſſizes publikely read.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And further, the Court conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and commending the paines, care, and travell, taken by the <hi>Relator</hi> in bringing that cauſe to judgement, and being ſatisfied upon the hearing of the cauſe, that the poore of the pariſh and the Miniſter there had beene ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally damnified by the defendant; Their Lordſhips did farther order and decree.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That the ſaid defendant ſhould pay unto the ſaid <hi>Relator</hi> one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounds for recompence of his travaile, beſides his coſts of ſuite.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:1301:49"/>
5 That hee ſhould pay unto the Miniſter of the Pariſh one hundred bounds.</p>
            <p n="6">6 That hee ſhould pay unto the poore of the Pariſh one hundred pounds to bee diſtributed to and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them at the diſcretion of the foure next Iuſtices of peace adjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſaid Towne.</p>
            <p n="7">7 And laſtly, the Court did or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that the defendant ſhould within two yeares after, repaire and build againe all the ſaid farme-houſes with their outhouſes, and the ſaid Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mill fit for habitation and uſe, as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly they were, and ſhould reſtore the lands formerly uſed and let, with the ſame farmes, unto the farme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes againe, and let and demiſe the ſame ſeverall farmes to ſeverall Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants for reaſonable rents, ſuch as the Country would afford, and that all the ſaid lands, ſhould be againe plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up and uſed to tillage, as formerly it had been.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:1301:50"/>
As by the decree remaining of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord in that honourable Court may plainely appeare; The true contents whereof are here ſet downe, that as it was publiſhed at the Aſſizes for an example in that Countrie, the benefit thereof may hereby redound to all the Counties of his Majeſties domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>53</label> I have the rather ſummarily tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the ſeverall points and bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of this decree for theſe reaſons; That every well affected Subject may diſcern the ſingular wiſdome of the Lords of his Majeſties moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable privy Counſell, and their aſſiſtants in that great Court: The Prayers of the Church we well hope are not in vaine; <hi>That it may pleaſe him to indue the Lords of the Councell and all the Nobility, with grace, wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and underſtanding.</hi> And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Gods ſpeciall indowments con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred on them, and on their <hi>Head</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der CHRIST, the <hi>Ship Royall</hi> of our <hi>State</hi> could not be ſo religiouſly,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:1301:50"/>providently, and proſperouſly ſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as it is: Methinkes when I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderately weigh the Compoſition of this decree, all parts of Iuſtice ſeeme here to be included.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Here is <hi>punition,</hi> 1. by impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, 2. by fine, 3. by publike acknowledgment.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Here is <hi>remuneration</hi> to the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>Relating,</hi> for diſcovering, and bringing the offendor to the publike ſeate of Iudgement.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Here is <hi>compenſation,</hi> 1. to the Miniſter, 2. to the poore of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, for the detriment and damage by them reſpectively ſuſteyned ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the circumſtances of the cauſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4 And laſtly here is <hi>reparation</hi> and <hi>reſtitution,</hi> which concernes the Common weale, 1. in repairing and reedifying the farmes, 2. in reſtoring the Land formerly uſed and let with them, 3. in letting and demizing the ſame farmes to ſeverall Tennants at reaſonable rents, 4. in converting
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:1301:51"/>the land to tillage againe</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>54</label> As in GODS ſentence, the <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum culpae</hi> was anſwered with the <hi>malum poenae;</hi> So it is fully accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed in this decree; for hereby <hi>All</hi> that any way ſuffered 1. <hi>King,</hi> 2. <hi>Church,</hi> 3. <hi>Common weale,</hi> 4. <hi>Poore,</hi> are all righted and ſalved, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it deſerves the more earneſt preſſing, firſt for the comfort of thoſe who grieve and grone under the burthen of this oppreſſion, that, though they be remote in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try from the eye of ſuperior Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, yet in the particulars of this decree, they may <hi>tanquam in perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cillis</hi> behold a farre off the vigilant care which his Majeſty and his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Councell have of the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt member of his <hi>Common weale:</hi> Secondly that others delinquents of the ſame ranke and quality, may <hi>tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam in ſpecule,</hi> as in a looking-glaſſe, view their owne <hi>evill</hi> of ſinne, and juſtly expect the ſame <hi>evill</hi> of pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhment.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:1301:51"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>55</label> That no men may lull them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves aſleepe with the conceipt of ſecurity, and that his highneſſe Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects who feele the ſmart of this miſchiefe, may have no cauſe to diſtruſt the continuance of his care, his <hi>goodneſſe</hi> hath of late directed ſeverall Commiſſions into moſt Counties of the Kingdome, out of the high Court of Chancery, I ſhall but briefly touch ſome ſpeciall points therein.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the motives which induced his Majeſty thereunto; His intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence that in diverſe parts of his Kingdome, very many Meſſuages and Manſion houſes (which had been for many yeares paſt habitations for husbandmen, farmers, and others exerciſed in tillage) did now remaine in decay, ruinous, deſtroyed, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inhabited, and the farmes and errable lands ſevered and divided from the houſes whereto they belonged, and great quantities of ſuch errable land,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:1301:52"/>have beene converted from culture into paſture, whereupon great waſt, and <hi>depopulation</hi> of Towns, Villages, Pariſhes and Hamlets in diverſe parts of his Kingdome have inſued, and are like dayly, more and more to increaſe to the diſhonour and preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of his Majeſty and his Crowne, and to the dammage and detriment of his people and whole Realme.</p>
            <p>Secondly, his Majeſties readineſſe to meete with ſuch miſchiefs, and to provide for the welfare of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and his people, by aſſigning and appoynting certaine Commiſſioners in moſt parts of his Kingdome, and giving unto them full power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority under his great Seale, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire by the oathes of good and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men, aſwell within liberties as as without, as alſo by the depoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of any credible witneſſes, to be called and examined upon their oathes, and by all other waies and meanes, and to make Certificate of the Inquiſitions taken before them, into the Chancery.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:1301:52"/>
Thirdly, the Subject of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry: What and how many Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughes, Townes, Villages, Pariſhes, Hamlets, Farmes, Farmehouſes or other Meſſuages or houſes, ſince the tenth yeare of the late <hi>Queene Eliz.</hi> have beene and now are <hi>depopulated,</hi> waſted, deſtroyed and ruinated, or converted from the habitation of husbandmen to other uſes, and what lands and Tenements have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted from tillage and plowing to other uſes, with diverſe other parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular clauſes and branches.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, a Command unto the Commiſſioners, to give notice unto all perſons, who claime title to any Lands or Tenements ſo waſted, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>populated, or ſeparated, either as heires or purchaſers, or by or under any perſon committing ſuch depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulation, and waſte, their Farmers or Aſſignes: That within a time limited by the Commiſſioners, or any two, or more; They, and every of them, doe reſpectively cauſe to bee re-edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:1301:53"/>and repaired, all and ſingular the ſaid houſes of husbandry, and all the ſeparated lands to be reſtored to the houſes, and that the lands converted from tillage to paſture and other un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull uſes, bee againe reſtored to tillage, and to admit of husbandmen to be Tenants to thoſe houſes, <hi>prout hactenus fieri conſuetum fuerit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>56</label> That his Majeſty hath full and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute power, to award ſuch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions for the good and benefit of his Kingdomes welfare, I thinke none ſo diſloyall as to doubt, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the exigence of the preſent times, for the better preparing of his intended reformation without a lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall imitation of former preſidents: <hi>In novo caſu novum apponendum eſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medium,</hi> variety of caſes muſt have variety of remedies; The wiſedome of a Parliament or a State may fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee an inſuing evill, and they may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act a prohibiting of it, and a proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſome paine and penalty againſt it, but they can never provide <hi>de fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:1301:53"/>is contingentibus</hi> of future circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances and contingencies, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>ubi non eſt directa lex, standum eſt arbitrio Iudicis,</hi> where a direct po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Law cannot meet with an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence in the very apple of the eye, the defect muſt be ſupplied by an arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Iudgement according to the circumſtances and occurencies of things. Let all the Statutes that ever were made, againſt the decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of houſes of husbandry and til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, be ſtrictly inſpected, and not any one of them either did or ever could preſcribe ſuch a proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable remedy, for ſuch a crime in all things, as the ſentence of that great Iudgement ſeat hath done.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>57</label> By the Statute of 5. and. 6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. intituled, <hi>An act for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of tillage, and increaſe of corne;</hi> It was ordeyned that his then Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, his Heires and Succeſſors, at his and their will and pleaſure, ſhould from time to time, direct his and their
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:1301:54"/>ſeverall Commiſſions under the great Seale of England, to ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as it ſhould pleaſe them, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire by the oathes of a ſufficient Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, what Lands and Tenements in every Towne, Pariſh, Village, or Hamlet within the limits of their charge, had at any time or times ſince the firſt yeare of King <hi>Henery</hi> the eight beene converted and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from tillage to paſture, and was then, or then after ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued and occupied in paſture, and to certifie the preſentment thereof into the Court of Chancery with convenient ſpeed, to bee thence deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered over into the Court of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, there to remaine amongſt the Records of the ſame Court, to the end that Statute might bee the more diligently and indifferently put in execution.</p>
            <p>By the Statute of 2. and 3. <hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>Mary cap.</hi> 2. intituled, <hi>An act for the reedifying of decayed houſes of husbandrie, and for the increaſe of til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage,</hi>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:1301:54"/>citing the Law of 4. <hi>Henery</hi> 7. which is before largely recited, it was ordayned that the like Commiſſions in effect ſhould be awarded, and that the Commiſſioners ſhould have full power and athority, to enquire, heare and determine, by the oathes of twelve men, or by information, or other lawfull wayes or meanes, all and ſingular defaults and offences, committed or done ſince the feaſt of Saint George the Martyr, in the twentieth yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, or then after ſhould be committed or done, aſwell contrary to the tenor and effect of the ſaid former act (4. <hi>Henery</hi> 7.) as contrary to one other <hi>act</hi> of 7. <hi>Henery</hi> 8. intituled, <hi>An act to avoyd letting downe of houſes,</hi> and alſo to enquire, heare, order, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine by the ſaid wayes and means of and concerning all grounds what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever converted from tillage to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture ſince the ſayd feaſt, or then after to bee converted from tillage to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, and alſo of all ground in or
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:1301:55"/>neare any corne fields newly uſed or imployed ſince the ſayd feaſt, or then after newly to be uſed, imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and converted to the keeping of Conies, not being a lawfull warren, and whereby the Corne of any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, other then the owner of the ſame Conies ſince the ſayd feaſt had been, or then after ſhould bee, deſtroyed or conſumed; And that the ſaid Commiſſioners ſhould and might bind by Recognizance the perſons offending, and guilty in any of the foreſaid decaies or defaults in ſuch ſummes of Money, as to the Commiſſioners ſhould ſeeme rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, for the reedifying of ſuch decayed houſes, and for the convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſuch grounds from paſture to tillage againe, and for the diminiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and deſtroying of Conies within ſuch convenient time, as the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners ſhould thinke meete, limit and appoint; with many clauſes and proviſoes in the ſayd Statute at large expreſſed.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:1301:55"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>58</label> By this every man may ſee that his now Majeſties proceeding to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire by way of Commiſſion, is no innovated thing (as ſome would mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure and pretend) but warranted by former examples, though different in the manner and forme, according to the difference of times; That of <hi>K. E.</hi> was to inquire and certifie; This of. <hi>K. Phi.</hi> and <hi>Q. M.</hi> to inquire, heare and determine.</p>
            <p>In this Statute there is one clauſe of moderation in theſe words. <hi>And for aſmuch as it is like to bee that ſome ground converted from tillage into pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, is divided into ſeverall ſmall par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells, remaining and being in divers and ſeverall mens hands, ſo that any one part will not be ſufficient to keepe a plow upon: and for that ſome grounds have beene tilled for the deſtroying of moſſe, buſhes, browne firs, heath, and not onely to be continued in tillage and ſuch like, and that alſo ſome demeanes in the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the owners have beene divided to ſundry occupiers, who have tilled the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:1301:56"/>ſame, not being commonly uſed to til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, before the ſaid feaſt of</hi> S. <hi>George: and for that divers other particular ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes may fortune to bee, which the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall purveiance of this Statute cannot remedy without greater hurt then good to be done by the ſame: and for that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in ſome places of this Realme it is not neceſſary the purveying of this eſtatute, to extend and to be fully executed, but in ſome places, and upon ſome occaſions or cauſes, it may more conveniently bee ſpared then put in ure, and is therefore neceſſary to referre ſuch things with all other circumstances, to the diſcretion of the Commiſsioners who may more perfectly underſtand the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>59</label> By this every man may collect, that no poſitive Law can bee ſo pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually made, as to adapt a cure for every civill diſeaſe, but muſt admit of a temper and qualification in ſome things, aſwell as an agravation in other things, according to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervenience of circumſtances: and therefore there was a power of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:1301:56"/>left unto the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</p>
            <p>But this <hi>evill</hi> being now growne great, and in favour and alliance with the greateſt men of a Country, the providence of his Majeſty and the <hi>State,</hi> hath by this Commiſſion only delegated a power to inquire and certifie, but not to determine, reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that to the diſcretion of himſelfe and his ſacred Councell who never confine their Iudgements to the <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> but the <hi>facts</hi> of men, and <hi>ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum allegata &amp; probata.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is another proviſion in that Law of <hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> in theſe words: <hi>And bee in enacted by the au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thority aforeſaid, that if any perſon or perſons, ſhall bee condemned or charged with or for any offence, that hee or they ought not to bee charged withal, by this act or by any of the foreſaid former Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes: That then the ſaid party or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſhall and may have his or their tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe and remedy therefore in the Star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber before the Councell there.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:1301:57"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>60</label> Hence is to bee inferred, that no Law can bee ſo wiſely woven and contexed, but will neede ſome inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation and explanation; And to whom doth the interpretation of the Lawes belong, but to the King, aſſiſted with his Honourable Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, and to the Reverend Iudges un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him. There is no <hi>Act</hi> done by the body of the Councell, but is preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be the <hi>Act</hi> of the King; In the time of <hi>Ed.</hi> the 3. <hi>Thorpe</hi> and other grave Iudges would not in caſes of difficulty deliver their finall Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, untill they had reſorted to the Lords of the Councell; Of caſes in that kinde, the yeare bookes in his Raigne are plentifull.</p>
            <p>This Statute, according to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of former times, ſeems to refer the party grieved to a remedy by way of traverſe and defence in the Star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber, a <hi>Court</hi> conſiſting of the greateſt Lords of the Honourable Councell, ſpirituall and temporall, reverend Iudges and other aſſiſtants.
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:1301:57"/>Whither ſhould there then bee any refuge, either for the interpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or moderation of poſitive Lawes (in the vacancy and ceſſation of the great <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi>) but unto this <hi>Court,</hi> where <hi>Kings</hi> themſelves have often vouchſafed to ſit in perſon?<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>61</label>
            </p>
            <p>His now M<hi rend="sup">ts</hi> providence and Iuſtice in diſperſing his ſaid Commiſſions, cannot take ſo good effect, if the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and <hi>Country</hi> (for redres of whoſe grievances they are awarded) be not dextrous and carefull in performing their duties of inquiry &amp; diſcovery, the <hi>Cmmoiſsioners</hi> are injoyned under their faith &amp; legiance to diſcharge the truſt in them repoſed; and all his M<hi rend="sup">ts</hi> Subjects, aſwell officers as others by the laſt clauſe of the <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſsion,</hi> are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to be attending, ayding, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting unto them, ſo often as they ſhall be thereunto ſummoned.</p>
            <p>I cannot therefore paſſe by thoſe good and <hi>lawfull men</hi> of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, who not only by vertue of their naturall and legall legiance, but alſo,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:1301:58"/>by a Sacramentall tye and bond, are or ſhall bee ingaged and charged to inquire of thoſe offences in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try without a monitory caution, that they imitate eſpecially, one of the properties preſcribed by <hi>Iethro,</hi> his Counſell to <hi>Moſes</hi> in ſelecting his Rulers of the people to be <hi>viri fortes, able men, non fortitudine corporis,</hi> but <hi>animi,</hi> not in ſtrength of body, but ſtrength of <hi>minde,</hi> not to feare the faces of men, not of a Land-lord, not of a potent man (were he a Liveten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant or greater) in a Country. <hi>Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude</hi> is one of <hi>Tullie</hi> his cardinall ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, it baniſheth all ſordid and ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh feare; It was an old complaint, that, <hi>Lawes</hi> were <hi>aranearum telis ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,</hi> like Cobwebs, wherein the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler flies are caught, great ones breake forth: Surely our Laws are not ſuch of <hi>themſelves,</hi> and moſt ſure it is, that our ſuperiour ſeats of <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi> are not ſo eaſily paſſed through, but that they will ſeize and hold the moſt griping and rapacious, bird, or
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:1301:58"/>beaſt; And with them is obſerved aſwell the practize as the <hi>rule.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Indè ortae leges, ne fortior omnia poſſet.</q>
            <p>But it is the abuſe of bad men, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the <hi>cowardiſe</hi> and <hi>puſilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity</hi> of thoſe who ſhould be <hi>probi &amp; legales homines,</hi> for want of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting and bringing offendors un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the eye of <hi>Law,</hi> that the <hi>Lawes</hi> are ſo much diſeſteemed: Such men who are ſo regardleſſe of their alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, ſo careleſſe of their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and reſpectleſſe of their oathes, that they will not ſee and diſcover the deſolations and greevances of their Country, are themſelves a <hi>gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance</hi> to the Country, and enemies to the King and State.</p>
            <q>— Hoſtis eſt,<note place="margin">Sen. in. Her. fur.</note> quiſquis mihi non monſtrat hoſtem—</q>
            <p>He is a foe unto me that diſcovers not my foe: A man may aſmuch tranſgreſſe in conniving at, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:1301:59"/>an offence, as the offender himſelfe in the acting of it, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may juſtly expect a proportion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able puniſhment.</p>
            <p>This may ſuffice for a briefe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance to the <hi>Iurors,</hi> whereof the Counſtables and other Country Officers may partake. I ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all with a Caution to Farmers and Husbandmen, and then draw to an end.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>62</label> They may obſerve by what hath paſſed before, that the labour of <hi>Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> was the firſt work injoyn'd unto man after the fall, renewed upon the renewing of the world in <hi>Noah</hi> and his poſterity, that it hath been highly honoured and priviledged amongſt all Nations, that it is moſt pretious in the eſteeme of our lawes and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and with what circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection &amp; watchfulnes his gracious Majeſty and his honorable Councell have proceeded for the upholding &amp; maintaining of it, and puniſhing all ſorts of delinquents againſt it; Will
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:1301:59"/>it not well beſeeme them to make themſelves fitly deſerving, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of ſo great a favour? The way to do it, is to act their part of <hi>diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butive Iuſtice,</hi> in bringing their corne and graine chearfully into the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets for ſupply of the poore and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers at reaſonable prices, and not to hide and hoard it up, to expect, nay to make and raiſe up a dearth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>63</label> I cannot chooſe but under favour tell them their fault, <hi>ingens crimen,</hi> a very great fault, they are growne to be the common favourers of Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtallers and Ingroſſers, and foſterers of an unruly generation of Maltma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, and by conſequence of a perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious number of <hi>Alehouſes,</hi> who have all a dependency one upon the other.</p>
            <p>It is a common practice, <hi>Et malum quo communius, eo pejus,</hi> for a Malt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker to reſort to a farmors houſe, &amp; after a ſcrutiny made what ſtore of barly he hath in his hands and poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, he preſently deales with the hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman to bring a ſample of it to
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:1301:60"/>market in a quantity of foure or five buſhels, and there he will bargaine for all the reſt in mow or barne, though it be five hundred quarters, to be threſhed out and brought home to his houſe, vainely flattering him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with this conceipt, that becauſe the compact was made for it in the marker, and earneſt there given, it is a lawfull buying, and not within the compaſſe of <hi>forestalling</hi> or <hi>ingroſsing, Pereant artes &amp; artifices:</hi> Let all ſuch who by theſe wilie and wicke ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, goe about to Circumvent the true intention of the Law, periſh with their owne devices: as it is the tricke of a foreſtalling Maltmaker, ſo is it as frequent with Bakers, Bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and other foreſtallers of Wheat and other graine at the houſes of huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>64</label> This evill hath ſo long dwelt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, that the offendors are ready to preſcribe uſe and cuſtome; they have been well met withal in the County of <hi>Norfolke,</hi> and other places
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:1301:60"/>by ſeverall Cenſures and Decrees of the honourable Court of Starcham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, made in the terme of S. <hi>Michaell</hi> in the ſeventh yeare of his Highneſſe Raigne, one eſpecially xxiij of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember, in the ſame terme, whereby ſome delinquents were ſentenced for contracting with Corne-maſters up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on market dayes for great quantities of Corne, and afterwards cauſing the ſame to be brought home to their houſes, as by the decree of the Court may appeare.</p>
            <p>It hath not onely infected thoſe parts, but like a venemous humor hath ſpread its infection through the veynes of the body of the whole Kingdome, and poyſoned almoſt the life bloud of government, eſpecially in many parts of our Weſterne regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, where it hath crept into borough Towns and Corporations, and there ſojournes in the houſes of Magiſtrats and Aldermen, who being expreſly required by his Majeſties Articles and directions publiſhed for the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:1301:61"/>good of his people in the yeare 1630 to take care for the ſuppreſſing of Maltſters; did in affront thereunto, take up and exerciſe the trade them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, having great means and other trades to live by.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>65</label> Whereſoever there are exceſſe of Maltſters, there will be a greater ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of Alehouſes, and I may be bold to ſay that the one ingenders the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but it is a ſpurious and unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full birth and brood; The Maltſter commonly truſteth the poore Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe keeper with a brewing of mault before hand, upon ſome ſlender ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, the vent of that muſt uſher in and pay for the next, and ſo ſtill keep a courſe beforehand, and it is very frequent, that one Maltſter hath un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his protection and command at leaſt ſixe or ſeven tiplers, either by connivence, or unlawfull licence, that ſhall moſt of them utter for him at leaſt thirty buſhells of mault a weeke one weeke with another; So outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious is the one in his oppreſſion by
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:1301:61"/>foreſtalling and ingroſſing, and ſo waſtfull and diſordered the other in their inordinate tipling, that ſcarce can a poore man buy a peck of barly in a market day for his money, and not five barley loves for the ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of a hungry multitude (if neede required) to bee found in a whole Country.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>66</label> This miſchiefe would be preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, if the Farmers and Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men would decline all ſiniſter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts with ſuch kind of men, and not ſell and deliver their Corne at their private houſes, but with cheereful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe bring it into the open market: <hi>Emporium eſt optima aeſtimatrix re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum;</hi> No kind of Graine, Victuall, or other vendible mercimony can be ſo truly valued and eſtimated, as in Faires or Markets overt, where there is a plentifull concourſe of buyers; Markets are either by grant from the King, or by ancient preſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; The Common Lawes of this Land have ever had the well uſing
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:1301:62"/>and ordering of them in great e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme.</p>
            <p>To which end and purpoſe the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Clarke of the market being very ancient, was firſt ordeyned to take care, and to view and inquire that all weights and meaſures bee agreeable to the Kings Standard in his Exchequor at Weſtminſter, and that all Corne and Victuall be ſold by ſuch, and by no other, and diverſe good Lawes have been made for ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing and obſerving the aſſize of bread and beer, according to the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes of Corne in the markets adjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; Of theſe things I have more amply treated elſewhere.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>67</label> The husband man muſt not onely bring his Corne into the market, but he muſt ſend the beſt, and not the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuze, he muſt not ſell it in a pinching, ſcant, or deceitfull meaſure, he muſt not keepe it up in muzled bags in the market, for colour and a ſhowe only, and not with any intention to ſet it to ſale, he muſt not uſe any art or ſhift
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:1301:62"/>to inhaunce the price of his Corne, and rather then he will ſell it at the ordinary price in the market, ſlide it into ſome privat corner, to remaine for a dearer ſale: It is not long ſince that a Country man ſtanding by his Corne in a market, and obſerving the price that day to bee more moderate then his covetuos mind expected, did with ſome fury and indignation, cloſe up his bags, conveigh them away, and fearefully ſweare, that he would keepe his Corne till Mice had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured it, rather then he would vent it at the rate of the market.</p>
            <p>Againſt all falſe, decitfull and hard hearted ſellers, the <hi>Prophet Amos</hi> denounceth a woefull Commina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, rowſing them up firſt with, <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite hoc qui conteritis pauperem, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficere facitis egenos terra, Dicentes, Quando tranſibit meſsis &amp; venum dabimus merces? Et Sabbatum, &amp; aperiemus frumentum, ut imminua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus menſuram, &amp; angeamus ſiclum, &amp; ſupponamus ſtater as doloſas, &amp; poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deamus
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:1301:63"/>deamus in argento egenos, &amp; pauperes pro calciamentis, &amp; quiſquilias fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti vendamus: Heare this ô yee that ſwallow up the needy, even to make the poore of the Land to faile, ſaying, when will the new Moone be gone, that we may ſell Corne, and the Sabbath, that we may ſet forth Wheat, making the Ephah ſmall, and the Shekell great, and fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſifying the ballances by deceipt, that we may buy the poore for ſilver, and the needy for a paire of ſhooes, yea and ſell the refuſe of the Wheate;</hi> Amos ca. 8. verſe 5, 6, 7. The ſentence followes: <hi>Shall not the Land tremble for this, and every one mourne that dwelleth therin?</hi> verſe 8. <hi>I will turne lla your feaſts into mourning, and all your ſongs into lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations,</hi> ver. 10.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>68</label> But ſithence the excellency of our dread Soveraigne hath vouchſafed ſo much tender care of tillage and cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as hath already produced a hop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full iſſue of future reformation, for the honour of his imperiall State, the advancement of the Church, and
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:1301:63"/>common good of all; It is much to be hoped, that the Farmers and Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen of his Kingdome will ſhake off thoſe Vipers, and have no fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with them in their wayes and courſes of oppreſſion, that they will not hide their Corne, and keepe it up to bee devoured by vermin, rather then at Competent rates, to diſperſe and diſtribute the bleſſings of the earth, amongſt his Majeſties people, at publike times and places appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Lawes and Government under which we live, that they will avoyd, all unwarranted tranſporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Corne, and in all things do, as they would bee done unto; And then,</p>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">Virg. Geor. l. 3.</note>O fortunatos nimium bona ſi ſua norunt Agricolas.</q>
            <p>Then the bleſſings of obedience ſhall be pronounced to them: <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſhalt thou be in the Citty, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſhalt thou be in the field, bleſſed ſhall be thy basket and thy ſtore, Deu.</hi> 28.3, 5.
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:1301:64"/>The <hi>King ſhall bee bleſſed in his people,</hi> and the people ſhall bee bleſſed in their King, <hi>wee ſhall not have cauſe to feare the faces of them that grind the faces of the poore,</hi> thoſe <hi>lapides mola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res; depopulators</hi> and racking Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lords. Nor ever take up that parable of lamentation, <hi>depopulatione vaſtati ſumus.</hi> The King ſhall cover us under the wings of his Royall and religious protection, and we ſhall render to him the dues of our faith and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, the Almighty ſhall cover us all with his bleſſing of peace and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and all ſhall goe well betweene King and Subject, better then <hi>prout hactenus fieri conſuetum fuerit.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="proceedings">
            <pb facs="tcp:1301:64"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1301:65"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1301:65"/>
            <head>IN CAMERA STELLATA CORAM CONCILIO IBIDEM, VI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CESSIMO TERTIO DIE Novembris, Anno Septimo <hi>Caroli Regis.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His day was brought to this Barre, <hi>William Taylor, Toby Pedder, Iohn Tub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin, Nicholas Browne, Robert Money, Iohn Boult,</hi> and <hi>Henery Cougham,</hi> againſt whom <hi>William Noy Eſquire,</hi> his <hi>Majesties At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turney</hi> generall, did informe <hi>ore tenus,</hi> on his Highneſſe behalfe, that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
<pb facs="tcp:1301:66"/>the care taken by his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> for this Realme, and Subjects ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, aſwel from the ſcarcity of <hi>Corne</hi> and graine, as from the exceſſive prizes and dearth of the ſame, and notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the wiſe directions given, and poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique orders deviſed and eſtabliſhed, and by Proclamation publiſhed, for the preventing of ſuch abuſes and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences which might otherwiſe hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, to the inhaunſing of the prices of <hi>Corne</hi> and graine, to the great prejudice of the rich, and even to the deſtruction of the poorer ſort of people; And not withſtanding, that the Lords of his <hi>Majeſties</hi> moſt honorable Privy <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell</hi> did take continuall care that his <hi>Majesties</hi> gracious and provident dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in that behalfe ſhould be put in due and conſtant execution, eſpecially
<pb facs="tcp:1301:66"/>this laſt yeare when as a great dearth and ſcarcity of <hi>Corne</hi> and graine was generally feared throughout this his Majeſties Kingdome, and therefore the better to prevent all inconvenience by the well ordering and diſpoſing of all ſuch <hi>Corne</hi> and graine, as God had bleſt this Kingdome withall, they did pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently provide, that firſt there ſhould be a generall and ſtrict reſtraint from tranſportation of all ſorts of <hi>Corne</hi> and graine out of this Kingdome, and that the Iuſtices of the peace in every Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſhould take care that the Markets ſhould be weekly ſerved by ſuch as had <hi>Corn</hi> to ſpare, and that none ſhould ſell out of market any <hi>Corne</hi> what ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, except it were to labourers, that ſo through the covetouſneſſe of thoſe that hoard up their <hi>Corne</hi> of purpoſe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haunce
<pb facs="tcp:1301:67"/>the prizes thereof, and make a dearth without cauſe, the Kings loving Subjects, the poore eſpecially ſhould not be pinched; ye the ſaid <hi>William Taylor, Tobby Pedder, Iohn Tubbin, Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las Browne, Robert Money, Iohn Boult,</hi> and <hi>Henery Cougham,</hi> not regarding the ſayd directions, nor deterred with the puniſhments which by the Laws and Statutes of this Realme may be inflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon ſuch offendors, but covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and unconſcionably deſiring to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich themſelves by the oppreſſion and loſſe of others, and endevoring to raiſe the exceſsive priſes of <hi>Corn,</hi> where there was no want (praiſed be God) of the ſame, but want of Charity and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in theſe and ſuch like wicked and wretched minded perſons, who ſtrive to inrich themſelves by ingroſsing of
<pb facs="tcp:1301:67"/>
               <hi>Corne,</hi> keeping their <hi>Corne</hi> up, and keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it out of market, that their ſtore and plenty might not be known, to the great contempt and breach of the ſaid Laws, Statutes, and Ordinances, and to the great offence of his Royall Majeſty, to whom nothing is more pleaſing then the peace, plenty, and proſperity of his people, and to the great ſcandall of all good and charitable minded per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, have this laſt yeare, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they had knowledge of the Orders and Proclamations<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> lately publiſhed concerning <hi>Corne</hi> and graine, bought great quantities of <hi>Corne</hi> out of the markets, having great ſtore of their own growing, and alſo forborne to bring any <hi>Corne</hi> at all into the markets all this laſt yeare, as by their ſeverall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminations may appeare, which he
<pb facs="tcp:1301:68"/>humbly praied might be read in <hi>Court,</hi> and that thereupon their Lordſhips would be pleaſed to inflict ſuch pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhment upon them for their ſaid of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences as they in their great wiſdomes ſhould hold fit; Wherupon the ſeverall examinations of the ſaid defendants were ſeverally ſhewed unto them, and acknowledged by them, and upon rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thereof, it appeared that the ſayd <hi>William Taylor</hi> having knowledge of his Majeſties ſayd Proclamation and book of orders, which came forth this laſt yeare by the Iuſtices of the Peace of the <hi>County</hi> of <hi>Northfolk,</hi> where the ſaid <hi>Taylor</hi> dwelt, for reſtraint of Maultage, did about <hi>Michelmas</hi> laſt was a twelve moneth buy twenty quarters of barley at ſeverall times in <hi>Burneham</hi> market, but the ſaid <hi>Corne</hi> was not in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket,
<pb facs="tcp:1301:68"/>nor ever brought to the market, but did not at any time carry or ſell any <hi>Corne</hi> at any market this laſt yeare, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he had five ſcore quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Barley, ten quarters of Wheat, and ten quarters of Rye, of his own, growing the laſt yeare, and had but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fifteen perſons in his houſe all that yeare. And it likewiſe appeared, that the ſaid <hi>Toby Pedder</hi> having the laſt yeare about forty quarters of Wheat, ten or twelve quarters of Rye, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove two hundred and threeſcrore Combs of Barley of his own growing, and having notice of his Majeſties <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation</hi> and of the booke of orders, ſet forth this laſt yeare, for ſerving the markets with <hi>Corne,</hi> did not ſend to or ſell any <hi>Corne</hi> at any market all the laſt yeare, but ſould about fifty quarters of
<pb facs="tcp:1301:69"/>Barely about Candlemas time laſt, to <hi>Matthew Hunt</hi> neer to Peterborough, and fifty quarters more to diverſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers at the water there, which was carried away, and delivered at Holme in Huntingdon ſhire, as he taketh it, and alſo bought this laſt yeare out of the market two quarters of wheat, and after he had notice of the ſaid Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation and booke of orders; bought five and twenty quarters of Barley, which he uſed for ſeed, but ſent not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in liew thereof to the market, and thirteen or fourteen quarters of Barley to mault which he put out to mault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to others, and did not uſe any maulting houſe of his owne the laſt yeare; and it likewiſe appeared that the ſaid <hi>Iohn Tubbin</hi> taking notice of the ſaid Proclamation and booke of
<pb facs="tcp:1301:69"/>orders for ſerving the market with <hi>Corne</hi> the laſt yeare, and having above thirty Combes of Rye, and above five or ſix hundred Combes of Batley, of his owne growing this laſt yeare, bought ten Combes of Rye after <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelmas</hi> laſt was twelvemonth, and five Combes of Rye more about <hi>Midſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> laſt, all out of the market, and ſent not any <hi>Corne</hi> at all to any market, nor ſold any thereby all the laſt yeare, but ſold to ſeveral perſons, from <hi>Farningha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> and <hi>Aldborough,</hi> 80. Combs of Barley about <hi>Candlemas</hi> laſt, and ſould 60. Combs of Barley more to a <hi>Cambridge</hi> ſhire man a little before Chriſtmas laſt, and ſold to one Baker of <hi>Colchester</hi> in <hi>Eſſex</hi> threeſcore Combs of Barley more about <hi>Michelmas</hi> laſt was twelve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>month, all which with ſeverall quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities
<pb facs="tcp:1301:70"/>of Barley were ſold out of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, and ſhipt away at <hi>Burneham</hi> by Sea, and exported to the ſeverall places aforeſaid (by licence from the Iuſtices) as by way of excuſe is in his examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſet forth, and alſo maulted ſixſcore quarters of Barley that yeare: And it likewiſe appeared that the ſaid <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas Browne</hi> of <hi>Walſingham</hi> in the Countie of <hi>Norfolke</hi> Gentleman, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving knowledge of the Proclamation and Orders aforeſaid, touching Corne and graine: and having nine ſcore quarters of Barley, foureteene quarters of Wheat, foureſcore quarters of Rye and Maſlyn, and threeſcore quarters of Oats of his owne growing, the laſt yeare carried not any <hi>Corne</hi> to the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, but twice the laſt yeare (for that as he alledgeth in his excuſe it is not the
<pb facs="tcp:1301:70"/>uſage of that Country to carry any <hi>Corne</hi> to the market, and at thoſe times when he did carry it to the market he brought it back againe, for that none came to buy the ſame as he alleageth, but the ſaid <hi>Browne</hi> did buy threeſcore quarters of Barley and part thereof, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with a great quantity of his own, he maulted by licence of the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices as he alledgeth, and by like li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence ſould the ſame, ſome into <hi>Yorke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> ſome to <hi>Molden</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and the reſt to Brewers in and neere <hi>Walſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and likewiſe maulted all his <hi>Oats,</hi> and ſould them to <hi>Brewers,</hi> in and neer <hi>Walſingham,</hi> and of his Wheat he ſpent only foure quarters in his family, and ſould the reſt to the <hi>Bakers</hi> of <hi>Walſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> but neither bought or ſould any in the market as he ought to have done,
<pb facs="tcp:1301:71"/>only he contracted for the <hi>Corne</hi> he bought, with <hi>Corne</hi> growers upon the market day at <hi>Walſingham,</hi> who ſhortly after brought it to his houſe, and there received their mony, and it likewiſe appeared that the ſaid <hi>Robert Money</hi> of <hi>Wells</hi> in the County of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke</hi> Gentleman, having knowledge of the ſaid Orders and Proclamation publiſhed concerning <hi>Corn</hi> and graine, and having twelveſcore Combs of <hi>Barley,</hi> betwixt forty and fifty Combs of <hi>Wheat,</hi> and about fifty Combs of <hi>Rye</hi> and <hi>Maſlin</hi> of his own growing, the laſt yeare did not carry any <hi>Corne</hi> to the market to be ſold, but ſayth he ſpared thirty Combe of <hi>Wheat</hi> out of his own proviſion, and ſent the ſame to <hi>London</hi> in the midle of the yeare, and ſold the ſame there at the beſt rate he
<pb facs="tcp:1301:71"/>could get, which was thirty ſhillings the Combe, and alſo ſould threeſcore Combe of <hi>Barley</hi> to one <hi>Pemberton</hi> of <hi>Ipſwich,</hi> which the ſaid <hi>Pemberton</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed he had warrant from ſome of the Iuſtices of <hi>Suffolke</hi> to buy for the poore of <hi>Ipſwich,</hi> and further affirmed that he had warrant from ſome of the Iuſtices of the peace of the ſaid Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Norfolke,</hi> to export the ſaid graine from his houſe to <hi>Ipſwich,</hi> but the ſaid <hi>Robert Money</hi> did not ſee either of the ſaid warrants, and yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing carrid the ſaid <hi>Corne</hi> in Carts to the Seaſide to be conveyed from thence to <hi>Ipſwich.</hi> And further it appeared that the ſaid <hi>Iohn Boulte</hi> late of <hi>Wells</hi> in the County of <hi>Norfolk</hi> Gentleman, having knowledge of the ſaid Orders, and <hi>Proclamation</hi> late publiſhed concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="tcp:1301:72"/>
               <hi>Corne</hi> and graine, and having the laſt yeare fifty Combe of <hi>Barley,</hi> and above thirty Combe of <hi>Wheate</hi> of his owne growing, and having a Family of fourteen perſons, did buy nineſcore Combe of <hi>Barley</hi> more which he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted for at <hi>Burneham</hi> market, &amp; had the ſame ſent home to his houſe, and there paid the money for the ſame, and alſo bought forty Combe of <hi>Rye</hi> of another <hi>Corne</hi>-maſter which he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted for at <hi>Falkenham</hi> market, and had it ſent home to his houſe and there paid the money for the ſame, but ſince harveſt laſt was twelvemonth, did not bring any <hi>Corne</hi> to the market to be ſould, for that as he alledgeth in his excuſe two of the Iuſtices did give leave that the poore, and handicrafts men of the towne being provided
<pb facs="tcp:1301:72"/>for, the ſaid <hi>Boult</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Corne</hi>-maſters might diſpoſe of their <hi>Corne</hi> as they pleaſed, as alſo for that it is not uſuall in thoſe parts to bring <hi>Corne</hi> into the markets to be ſold, but to utter their <hi>Corne</hi> either in their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or by exportation to other remote places within the Kingdome, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe the ſaid <hi>Boult</hi> did mault a great quantity of the <hi>Barley</hi> he bought, and by Licence from the Iuſtices as he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leageth ſhipt the ſame away to <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>castle,</hi> and there ſold the ſame, and alſo ſould twenty Combe of his <hi>Wheat</hi> to one <hi>Arwaker</hi> of <hi>Chelmesford</hi> who brought a Licence from the Iuſtices of Eſſex and ſhewed the ſame to the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of <hi>Norfolke</hi> for his buying the ſame: And laſtly it appeared that the ſaid <hi>Henry Cougham</hi> of <hi>Wells</hi> in the
<pb facs="tcp:1301:73"/>ſaid County of <hi>Norfolke</hi> Gentleman, having knowledge of the ſaid Orders and <hi>Proclamation</hi> concerning <hi>Corne</hi> and graine publiſhed as aforeſaid, and having in harveſt was a twelvemonth fiveſcore Combs of Barley, twenty Combe of Rye, and twenty Combe of Wheat of his owne growing, did not ſince harveſt aforeſaid carry any <hi>Corne</hi> to the market to be ſould, but bought ſixſcore Combe of Wheat of ſeverall <hi>Corne</hi>-maſters dwelling neere the ſaid towne of <hi>Wells,</hi> and delivered the ſame to <hi>Francis Carter</hi> of London <hi>Baker,</hi> and <hi>Samuel Satchfield</hi> of London <hi>Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer,</hi> which in his excuſe he alleageth he did by vertue of a warrant from the <hi>Lord Mayor,</hi> and two other Iuſtices of the peace of the City of London, but upon reading the ſaid warrant, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth
<pb facs="tcp:1301:73"/>that the ſaid <hi>Cougham</hi> was not required or authoriſed to buy any <hi>Corne</hi> of the ſaid parties for the uſe of the ſaid City of London, but to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey <hi>Corne</hi> to London which was bought before by the ſaid <hi>Carter</hi> and <hi>Satchfield,</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Cougham</hi> did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the laſt yeare buy twelve ſcore Combe of Barley at ſeverall times in ſeveral places, and maulted al the ſame, as alſo the Barley of his own grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, excepting about threeſcore and ten Combe, with twenty Combe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he ſowed his land, and by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Iuſtices he kept in ſtore the fifty Combe reſidue for the poore of <hi>Wells,</hi> and about forty or fifty combe of the mault he made he ſent to New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtle, and the reſt to Ipſwich, and that he alleageth in his excuſe he did by
<pb facs="tcp:1301:74"/>Order from the Iuſtices under their hands. Vpon reading of all which their ſayd examinations the ſaid delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents at the barre were ſeverally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded what anſwer they could make to their ſaid offences who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devoured to excuſe the ſame in ſuch ſort as ſome of them in their examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions had done by alleadging that it was not the uſage of that part of the Country to carry any <hi>Corne</hi> to the markets nor for any to buy at the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets in reſpect of the plenty of <hi>Corne</hi> in thoſe parts, and that after proviſion was made for the poore of the ſeverall Pariſhes and hundreds where they live, they had licence from the Iuſtices to diſpoſe of the reſt of their <hi>Corne</hi> as they pleaſed themſelves, and humbly craved the favour of this moſt hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb facs="tcp:1301:74"/>
               <hi>Court:</hi> And therupon the <hi>Court</hi> well weighing the nature and quality of their ſaid offences to be ſuch as juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſerved the cenſure of this moſt honourable <hi>Court</hi> conſidering the great perill wherunto the Commonwealth is ſubject, if the ſame ſhould encreaſe and continue the uncharitable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull hoarding up and ingroſſing of <hi>Corne</hi> and keeping their own from the markets being a great means to ariſe and continue the exceſsive prizes of <hi>Corne</hi> without any ſcarcity, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all the <hi>Court</hi> conſidering that all offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and miſdemeanors tending to the inhauncement of the prizes of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, eſpecially of <hi>Corne</hi> and Victuall to exceſsive rates, are great and generall oppresſions againſt the ancient and good Lawes of the Kingdome, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaving
<pb facs="tcp:1301:75"/> that theſe delinquents have not onely offended againſt the lawes and Statutes of this Realme made and provided aſwell againſt ingroſſers and hoorders up of <hi>Corne,</hi> and foreſtallers of markets, as againſt ſuch as ſhall pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctize or procure the raiſing of <hi>Corne,</hi> Victual or other commodities unto un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable prizes, but have alſo highly offended againſt his Majeſties Royall Proclamation, and the good and poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique Orders made and taken by the Lords of his Majeſties moſt honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Privy Councell for preventing the dearth and ſcarcity of <hi>Corne,</hi> and reliefe of the poore in times of dearth and ſcarſity, have therefore adjudged and decreed that the ſaid <hi>William Toby, Pedder, Iohn Tubbin, Nicholas Browne, Robert Money, Iohn Boult,</hi> and <hi>Henery
<pb facs="tcp:1301:75"/>Cougham,</hi> ſhall all and every of them for their offences aforeſaid ſtand and be committed to the Priſon of the Fleet, and pay a hundred pounds apeece for their ſeverall fines to his Majeſty, and withall the Court holding it fit to have ſome example made thereof in the County of Norfolke where all the ſaid defendants dwell, to the end other perſons of like uncharitable diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may take warning thereby, and bee deterred from offending in the like kinde hereafter, have therefore further ordred, adjudged, and decreed, that all the ſaid defendants ſhall at the next Aſſizes to be holden for the ſaid <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> ſeverally make their humble ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments of their offences pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely in the face of the Court, the Iudges and Iuſtices then there ſitting,
<pb facs="tcp:1301:76"/>but the <hi>Court</hi> doth forbeare to inflict any further corporall or ignominious puniſhment upon them, in reſpect their offences ſeeme to be ſomwhat quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the Licence given them by the Iuſtices, who ſhould and ought more ſtrictly to have required their obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the ſaid Proclamation and Orders, and not to have given way to the breach thereof, which their Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips hold a great offence in them, and worthy to be puniſhed, if it be true as the delinquents in their excuſes have pretended.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:1301:76"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
